<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<gpg-book local-id="A6424C_1" type="TRD"><content-metadata><title>Germs at Bay</title><subtitle>Politics, Public Health, and American Quarantine</subtitle><contributor role="author"><display-name>Charles Vidich</display-name><name-parts><last-name>Vidich</last-name><given-names>Charles</given-names></name-parts><author-info><p local-id="A6424C_2"><b>Charles Vidich</b> is a consultant and adviser on public health and bioterrorism issues and was appointed as a visiting scientist at the Harvard School of Public Health, working for ten years on national quarantine policy. He has numerous publications on occupational and environmental health and served as incident commander for the U.S. Postal Service’s national anthrax response in 2001–2002. He holds SM and MCP degrees from Harvard and has received numerous White House, EPA, and Postal Service awards for his environmental and anthrax response work. He serves on the Connecticut Council on Environmental Quality, appointed by the Speaker of the House.</p></author-info></contributor></content-metadata><print-pub-metadata><object-id id-type="ISBN" object-type="PBK">978-1-4408-7833-6</object-id><object-id id-type="ISBN" object-type="HC">978-1-4408-7834-3</object-id><imprint>ABC-CLIO, LLC</imprint><imprint-city>Santa Barbara</imprint-city><imprint-state>California</imprint-state><display-date>2021</display-date><cip><cip-line>Copyright © 2021 by Charles Vidich</cip-line><cip-line>All rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted, in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, or otherwise, except for the inclusion of brief quotations in a review, without prior permission in writing from the publisher.</cip-line><cip-line>Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data</cip-line><cip-line>Names: Vidich, Charles, author.</cip-line><cip-line>Title: Germs at bay : politics, public health, and American quarantine / Charles Vidich.</cip-line><cip-line>Description: Santa Barbara : ABC-CLIO, [2021] | Includes bibliographical references and index.</cip-line><cip-line>Identifiers: LCCN 2020034372 (print) | LCCN 2020034373 (ebook) | ISBN 9781440878336 (hardcover) | ISBN 9781440878343 (ebook)</cip-line><cip-line>Subjects: LCSH: Quarantine—United States—History. | Public health—United States.</cip-line><cip-line>Classification: LCC RA665 .V53 2021 (print) | LCC RA665 (ebook) | DDC 614.4/60973—dc23</cip-line><cip-line>LC record available at https://lccn.loc.gov/2020034372</cip-line><cip-line>LC ebook record available at https://lccn.loc.gov/2020034373</cip-line><cip-line>ISBN: 978-1-4408-7833-6 (print)</cip-line><cip-line>978-1-4408-7834-3 (ebook)</cip-line><cip-line>25 24 23 22 21	1 2 3 4 5</cip-line><cip-line>This book is also available as an eBook.</cip-line><cip-line>Praeger</cip-line><cip-line>An Imprint of ABC-CLIO, LLC</cip-line><cip-line>ABC-CLIO, LLC</cip-line><cip-line>147 Castilian Drive</cip-line><cip-line>Santa Barbara, California 93117</cip-line><cip-line>www.abc-clio.com</cip-line><cip-line>This book is printed on acid-free paper</cip-line><cip-line>Manufactured in the United States of America</cip-line></cip></print-pub-metadata><front><dedication local-id="A6424C_3"><p local-id="A6424C_4">To my wife, Clare, and my three sons, Jamie, David, and Paul</p></dedication><div local-id="A6424C_5" type="fm-extra"><page-start number="pgvii"></page-start><content-metadata><title>Contents</title></content-metadata><list type="simple"><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_6"><i>Acknowledgments</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_39"><display-text><i>ix</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_7"><i>Introduction</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_51"><display-text><i>xiii</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_8"><b>Chapter 1</b> The Quarantine Grab Beg <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_66"><display-text>1</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_9"><b>Chapter 2</b> Quarantine through the Generations: Five Stages of Practice <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_95"><display-text>11</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_10"><b>Chapter 3</b> Quarantine in the Colony <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_121"><display-text>22</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_11"><b>Chapter 4</b> The Inoculation Controversy <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_187"><display-text>45</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_12"><b>Chapter 5</b> Branding the Outcasts: Warning Out and Red Flags <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_221"><display-text>59</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_13"><b>Chapter 6</b> Large-Scale Sequestration <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_281"><display-text>77</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_14"><b>Chapter 7</b> The Revolutionary War and Its Aftermath: A New Perspective <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_305"><display-text>86</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_15"><b>Chapter 8</b> Yellow Fever and the Emergence of Boards of Health <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_386"><display-text>112</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_16"><b>Chapter 9</b> Boston Board of Health <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_456"><display-text>134</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_17"><b>Chapter 10</b> Vacination <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_474"><display-text>141</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_18"><b>Chapter 11</b> Yellow Fever Outbreak of 1819 and the Excesses of Quarantine <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_501"><display-text>150</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_19"><b>Chapter 12</b> Miasma Theory, Maritime Commerce, and Quarantine Restraints <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_519"><display-text>157</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_20"><b>Chapter 13</b> Der Island Quarantine Station <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_590"><display-text>179</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_21"><page-start number="pgviii"></page-start><b>Chapter 14</b> Cholera Contagion and the Resurrection of Quarantine <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_636"><display-text>193</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_22"><b>Chapter 15</b> Gallop’s Island <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_649"><display-text>197</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_23"><b>Chapter 16</b> The Evolution of the Cowpox Vaccine <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_677"><display-text>207</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_24"><b>Chapter 17</b> The Smallpox Epidemic of 1872 <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_710"><display-text>217</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_25"><b>Chapter 18</b> Germ Theory Reframes Quarantine <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_779"><display-text>238</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_26"><b>Chapter 19</b> Federal Solutions to Quarantine <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_814"><display-text>248</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_27"><b>Chapter 20</b> Boston’s Last Epidemics <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_847"><display-text>258</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_28"><b>Chapter 21</b> The End of Boston’s Maritime Quarantine Department <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_878"><display-text>267</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_29"><b>Chapter 22</b> Quarantine under U.S. Public Health Service <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_910"><display-text>283</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_30"><b>Chapter 23</b> Redefining Quarantine for the Twenty-First Century <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1000"><display-text>310</display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_31"><i>Appendix A: Chronology of Key American Quarantine Events, 1647–2020</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1071"><display-text><i>329</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_32"><i>Appendix B: Chronology of Nineteenth-Century Boston Quarantine Ordinances, 1822–1873</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1073"><display-text><i>339</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_33"><i>Appendix C: History of Boston’s Port Physicians, 1779–1915</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1075"><display-text><i>343</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_34"><i>Appendix D: Quarantine Decision Tree</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1076"><display-text><i>347</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_35"><i>Glossary</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1077"><display-text><i>349</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_36"><i>About Sources</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1206"><display-text><i>359</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_37"><i>Notes</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1252"><display-text><i>369</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item><list-item><p local-id="A6424C_38"><i>Index</i> <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_4485"><display-text><i>483</i></display-text></ref></p></list-item></list></div><div local-id="A6424C_39" type="fm-extra"><page-start number="pgix"></page-start><content-metadata><title>Acknowledgments</title></content-metadata><p local-id="A6424C_40">This book would not have happened without a series of chance encounters that opened me to consider quarantine as a critical tool for the twenty-first century. I am indebted to James Bromberg, MD, JD, MPH, for our endless days of studying quarantine at the Harvard School of Public Health (HSPH). Without his friendship and camaraderie, I would not have undertaken this book. Indeed, in my own experience, James Bromberg is one of the few attorney-physicians who fully grasps the importance of quarantine in the modern world.</p><p local-id="A6424C_41">In 2001, I had been working on the government’s response to the anthrax crisis in the postal system when I met Dr. Don Milton at the anthrax conference held at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta, Georgia. Through a series of discussions and subsequent meetings, I took a one-year limited leave from my normal duties in the government to pursue my interests in bioterrorism and infectious disease. Through Don Milton I met Drs. Jennifer Leaning and Arnold Howitt, who would later become my faculty advisers on a special project to investigate the application of quarantine to nineteenth-century communicable diseases. Laura Lynn Taylor, Jim Bromberg, and I spent a semester investigating the application of quarantine in New Orleans, San Francisco, Los Angeles, and Boston. Our research was taking place as the Asian SARS epidemic was emerging, which gave added impetus to our efforts.</p><p local-id="A6424C_42">After completing my degree program at the HSPH, I suggested an extension of my work to complete a more comprehensive investigation of the 1872 Boston smallpox epidemic. This epidemic had never been studied in detail, and yet it offered an enormous number of remarkable lessons for public health officials concerned with the twenty-first-century application of quarantine. HSPH accepted my request to pursue this scholarly investigation under the guidance of Jennifer Leaning. As a visiting scientist at HSPH, I have been deeply indebted to Jennifer Leaning for sponsoring my research <page-start number="pgx"></page-start>and suggesting ways of framing the quarantine project. She is nothing short of one of the most remarkable persons I have ever met—equally at ease in the world of medical history as she is in the world of real-time emergency response to medical disasters throughout the world. To have had this opportunity was certainly fortuitous and was enabled by my chance meeting with Don Milton.</p><p local-id="A6424C_43">I am deeply indebted to Rebecca Orfaly Cadigan and Anson Wright, both of whom spent considerable time and energy reviewing earlier versions of this manuscript and providing editorial and substantive suggestions. In the world of quarantine research, there are very few who have invested the energy and time in understanding these issues as well as Anson Wright and Rebecca Orfaly Cadigan. This book would not have been possible without their insightful comments.</p><p local-id="A6424C_44">I am also indebted to John Freitas for reviewing an early version of the manuscript and providing insightful comments about the history of Boston as only a true Bostonian could do. The discussion of island quarantine would not be as complete without his comments. Two other people who opened my awareness of Boston Harbor were Peter Tropeano, captain of Boston Waterbus Services, Inc., and Darryl Forgione of the Massachusetts Department of Environmental Conservation. Mr. Tropeano provided marine transportation to numerous Boston Harbor islands during the summer of 2005, and Mr. Forgione provided access to Gallop’s Island at a time when it was off limits to the public. Without their support it would not have been possible to connect the dots between nineteenth-century harbor geography and the landscape of today.</p><p local-id="A6424C_45">The amount of research required to complete this manuscript was formidable. There is no one library or research facility where all of the quarantine records for Boston or federal quarantine programs can be found. Indeed, over forty different libraries and research facilities were extensively consulted to prepare this history. Harvard’s Widener, Countway, Lamont, Pusey, Littauer, Law, and Houghton Libraries contained extensive records of the early history of Boston and the epidemics of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. The Countway Library of Medicine’s Rare Books collection was invaluable for tracing the nineteenth-century history of quarantine and the dual role of Harvard’s medical professors as consulting physicians to the city of Boston. I am indebted to Jack Eckert, reference librarian, and Peter Rawson, archivist, and their colleagues for supporting my research. In addition, Joseph Garver, reference librarian, and his colleagues at the Nathan Marsh Pusey Library assisted with access to the historic maps of eighteenth- and nineteenth-century Boston. These ancient maps were invaluable in depicting harbor channels, quarantine grounds, and island features that explained the geographic constraints faced by port physicians, harbor masters, and <page-start number="pgxi"></page-start>commanders when negotiating their way from Boston’s docks to its quarantine islands.</p><p local-id="A6424C_46">The Boston Public Library staff was of tremendous help in the completion of this book, particularly Henry Scannell, curator of microtext and newspapers. Mr. Scannell spent countless hours helping to identify smallpox cases and incidents of quarantine in eighteenth- and nineteenth-century Boston. The microtext files for the <i>Boston Globe</i>, the <i>Advertiser</i>, and the <i>Boston Herald</i> provided detailed coverage of the 1872 smallpox epidemic that was critical to the completion of this book.</p><p local-id="A6424C_47">The quarantine history of Boston cannot be told without access to federal records. In this regard, the National Archives and Records Administration (NARA) staff in College Park, Maryland, provided exceptional support with the identification and retrieval of Public Health Service records from the early twentieth century. David Pfeiffer went above and beyond the normal responsibilities of his job and pulled many Boston Quarantine Station files for my review during evening hours when I had the time available to scour the extensive federal records for Gallop’s Island.</p><p local-id="A6424C_48">Eva Murphy, reference librarian at the Massachusetts State House Library, was also extremely helpful in identifying laws, legislative histories, and statutes pertaining to the long history of quarantine in Massachusetts. As a result of her efforts and the efforts of her colleagues, important legal riddles concerning the promulgation and rescission of disease reporting laws in the nineteenth century and the reasons why quarantine laws influenced the outcome of the Revolutionary War in Boston have been solved. Another important source of crucial information on Boston’s history is Historic New England, previously known as the Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities (SPNEA). Emily Novak, librarian/archivist at the SPNEA, helped provide access to various old photographs and newspaper clippings that shed light on the history of Boston Harbor islands. Similarly, Chester R. Kennedy, executive director of the Public Health Museum in Tewksbury, Massachusetts, was extremely generous with his time and attention and provided expert guidance on the history of public health issues in Massachusetts. The Public Health Museum in Tewksbury is a rare gem for those interested in the history of public health in Massachusetts.</p><p local-id="A6424C_49">I was also fortunate to have the support and editorial services of my father, Dr. Arthur Vidich, during the early stages of preparing this manuscript. His comments and critiques of earlier manuscripts were invaluable and certainly improved the analysis of the political and social aspects of quarantine administration. His support was particularly meaningful insofar as he gave unstintingly his time despite the challenges of his failing health. Finally, I wish to thank Susan Morrison who thoroughly reviewed the manuscript and <page-start number="pgxii"></page-start>immeasurably improved the storyline—making what otherwise might be a dry topic accessible to a wider audience.</p><p local-id="A6424C_50">Most importantly, I wish to acknowledge the support of my wife, Clare, and my sons, Jamie, David, and Paul, all of whom let me spend years of my so-called free time on the pursuit of this book. Their sacrifices cannot go unmentioned. After all, someone had to take care of the routine matters of a household while I was lost in the bowels of Harvard’s Widener Library or the National Archives in Washington, DC.</p></div><div local-id="A6424C_51" type="fm-extra"><page-start number="pgxiii"></page-start><content-metadata><title>Introduction</title></content-metadata><p local-id="A6424C_52">Quarantine, as an invention of man, is the most primitive and universal instrument of defense against contagious disease epidemics. Almost universally maligned or ignored by historians, quarantine is like an iceberg with 90 percent of its secrets hidden from view in inaccessible archives of the government. The few American historians who have studied quarantine have skimmed its surface, dissuaded by the effort required to pull together vast amounts of primary source materials scattered all over the world. Yet, there is a rich history to be told. Quarantine has played a central role in the survival of colonial and postcolonial America and indeed remains central to our survival as a species. Boston as the oldest and most quarantine-tested city in America provides a rich historical record to delve into the origin and evolution of American public health strategies for controlling epidemic disease.</p><p local-id="A6424C_53">After spending many months self-quarantined off an undisclosed island along the eastern seaboard, I had the opportunity to reflect on the nearly four hundred years of American quarantine practice distilled from nearly twenty years of research at Harvard and throughout the world. Immersing myself in the history of American quarantine was a far greater task than I ever imagined. My research took me to quarantine islands throughout the United States, Europe, and the Caribbean, where the archaeological remains of maritime quarantine stations can still be found. In some locations, such as Boston’s Gallop’s Island, I found the names of port physicians carved into boulders almost as if they resisted their life’s work being lost to history. In other locations, such as Philadelphia, urban renewal transformed the city’s nineteenth-century quarantine station into the town hall of a Philadelphia suburb. Perhaps most importantly, working with a team of some of the most brilliant men and women I have ever known, I served in various capacities on the Unified Incident Command Center’s Rapid Response team, including as the incident commander, responsible for containing the 2001 anthrax attacks that spread the disease and fear across the nation. In working to <page-start number="pgxiv"></page-start>protect the health of the nation, I came to realize the challenge of dealing with so-called novel pathogens and how little was known about the proper role of quarantine. I have come to understand that quarantine is a mirror into the soul of each generation—reflecting its social, political, and medical values.</p><p local-id="A6424C_54">The history of American quarantine is one of fits and starts coincident with discoveries of disease transmission. If a disease was not considered communicable by inhalation or contact, quarantine was less likely to be imposed. However, many communicable diseases were not recognized as such, with devastating consequences for public health, such as the mismanagement of tuberculosis as a noncommunicable disease in nineteenth-century America.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1256"><display-text><sup>1</sup></display-text></ref> Communicable diseases often spread extremely rapidly, which is facilitated by overcrowding and highly congested living environments found in modern cities. Germs can travel from one person to another simply through a cough, kiss, or handshake or even by sharing common eating utensils. When a germ is both highly communicable and pathogenic, it becomes a public health threat, especially when cases multiply faster than resources become available to counter its spread. The African Ebola epidemic of 2014 and the COVID-19 pandemic of 2020 are cases on point. Epidemics inevitably overwhelm hospital resources and can lead to restrictions on social gatherings, school closings, and travel and even various forms of quarantine.</p><p local-id="A6424C_55">Quarantine has long relied on physical separation of the infected individual or vessel from the rest of society. For example, one early Massachusetts law required persons on infected vessels to be at least four rods, or sixty-six feet, away from any other person not on board. Other colonial laws required infected vessels to be quarantined at designated harbor moorings at least one mile from shore.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1258"><display-text><sup>2</sup></display-text></ref> These laws shared the belief that miasmas, or noxious air, could travel long distances and impact those in its downwind pathway. These same distancing principles, while dramatically altered by over one hundred years of bacteriological and viral research, still remain important public health strategies that complement the more confining principle of quarantine. Ironically, while neighborhood-based quarantines are less commonly used than in any previous period in American history, there are more communicable diseases known today than ever before, and more importantly, more diseases require quarantine, isolation, or special distancing strategies.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1260"><display-text><sup>3</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_56">Ebola has taught us the limitations of modern medicine. Not all pathogens can be controlled through antibiotics or antivirals, and it is under these unique conditions that quarantine rises to the top of public health priorities. Yet, each disease has its unique vulnerabilities to medicine and quarantine. Like medicine, quarantine works best when founded on evidence. Without insight into a pathogen’s trail of infection, we fall prey to voodoo public health strategies that create as many problems as they solve. Indeed, the <page-start number="pgxv"></page-start>search for the Holy Grail of disease transmission has spanned the history of quarantine in America, evolving in response to different types of epidemics each with its unique pathogen characteristics. Yet, this is not how our forefathers dealt with epidemics. Prior to the germ theory of disease, many contagions were grouped together as pestilential or contagious simply for lack of knowledge concerning its mode of transmission.</p><p local-id="A6424C_57">By clarifying the effective pathways of disease transmission, we shed new light not only on evolving quarantine principles but also on the unique events that delayed American acceptance of public hygiene and disease surveillance, leading to discriminatory immigration policies prohibiting entry of those with loathsome communicable disease. Quarantine, in brief, is intimately connected to America’s immigration control system as witnessed by the disease-based suspensions of immigration during the cholera epidemic of 1892 and COVID-19 pandemic of 2020.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1262"><display-text><sup>4</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_58">The failure to understand disease transmission—even in the twenty-first century—is the primary challenge we face, and it is even more challenging in the arena of novel pathogens where, by definition, we have limited knowledge of disease transmission dynamics. By following the trail of disease transmission, this book shows how quarantine concepts continue to evolve, reflecting contemporary social and political values and the nuances of exposure unique to each microbial threat.</p><p local-id="A6424C_59">The increasing interconnectedness of the world’s inhabitants has meant our potential exposure to highly communicable pathogens from distant lands can occur in less than twenty-four hours. Our public health and immigration systems are not capable of stopping such instantaneous invasions, and for many emerging diseases, there are no pharmaceutical remedies—think SARS, MERS, and COVID-19. During the twentieth century, this nation systematically dismantled its maritime quarantine program at a time when antibiotics seemed to offer a panacea to all diseases. In the fifty years following World War II, communicable disease was relegated to a lower-order public health priority. As a result, this generation of Americans has little understanding of quarantine and why it remains a critical public health tool.</p><p local-id="A6424C_60">Although quarantine has operated on the margins of modern society, it has been indispensable in stopping wave upon wave of smallpox, cholera, yellow fever, and typhoid epidemics.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1264"><display-text><sup>5</sup></display-text></ref> Its power and influence have not been determined by the face time in American history books or its regularity of use in combating epidemics.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1266"><display-text><sup>6</sup></display-text></ref> It appeals to our deep-rooted communal need for survival by seclusion from gruesome disease, possible death, or economic destruction. Indeed by the standards of the amount of air time it gets in nonpandemic years, quarantine would continue to be of little interest to the average person. It is said that history is written by the victors, and in this context the medical breakthroughs from twentieth-century vaccines, antibiotics, and antivirals have buried the contributions made by quarantine. Yet, quarantine <page-start number="pgxvi"></page-start>practice, which lost favor after World War II, became the nation’s new public health mantra in 2020 as a natural response to the rapidly changing environmental, political, and sanitary conditions throughout the world, including the onslaught of zoonotic diseases—such as COVID-19, the coronavirus disease that emerged in Wuhan, China, in December 2019.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1268"><display-text><sup>7</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_61">As the world’s population expands, increasing routine contact with exotic microbial forms of life, there has been a noticeable increase in zoonotic disease—where animals serve as the reservoir for infecting human beings.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1270"><display-text><sup>8</sup></display-text></ref> Hundreds of new zoonotic diseases have been discovered in the last fifty years as virologists, bacteriologists, and microbe hunters stomp through the African, South American, and Asian jungles in pursuit of the next deadly plague.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1272"><display-text><sup>9</sup></display-text></ref> Seeking the next pandemic, these hunters have discovered a range of highly mutable avian viruses, a host of mosquito-borne hemorrhagic fevers (including less lethal fevers such as zika, dengue, etc.), and the common Lyme disease spirochete.</p><p local-id="A6424C_62">With our improved understanding of disease transmission, twenty-first-century quarantine need not be “one-size-fits-all” approach. Quarantine should never be considered as simply a form of confinement. Innovations in modern medicine, engineering, and behavioral science research have expanded the principles of quarantine to also encompass what might be called “pathogen quarantine” or “pathogen exclusion” strategies, such as the use of personal protective equipment like face masks and personal hygiene or the use of mosquito repellent to thwart vector-borne diseases like yellow fever or malaria. Rather than confining people, the focus should be on confining disease vectors based on more detailed understandings of their pathways.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1274"><display-text><sup>10</sup></display-text></ref> For example, does the microbe enter the body through inhalation, skin contact, sexual intercourse, injection, or ingestion?</p><p local-id="A6424C_63">Diseases deemed to have unpredictable or unknown transmission characteristics are inevitably poorly understood.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1276"><display-text><sup>11</sup></display-text></ref> Similar challenges have also been faced by far more communicable diseases such as COVID-19, which by virtue of its novelty had no readily available vaccine during the early phase of the pandemic when disease containment was most critical. Under these circumstances, desperate people apply desperate measures, creating fear-driven strategies that have become one of the legacies of past unscientific applications of quarantine.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1278"><display-text><sup>12</sup></display-text></ref> It is like a sharp shooter in a dark room trying to shoot at something that he or she can’t see. Simplistic as this may sound, modern quarantine strategies continue to suffer from the dilemma of “needing to do something” even as there is uncertainty in the mode of disease transmission.</p><p local-id="A6424C_64">Telling the story of quarantine in America represents far more than a litany of its uses and abuses. This book explores the roots of quarantine practice in America, through the lens of Boston’s long history with epidemic disease, with the aim of elucidating its critical role in shaping modern <page-start number="pgxvii"></page-start>conceptions of epidemic response plans, disease surveillance, and immigration controls. The early years of this story are best told through the colonial and postcolonial public health practices of Boston since it was the leader in many of the most significant quarantine innovations in early America. Indeed, quarantine, as a public health tool, was exclusively a state and local responsibility prior to our Declaration of Independence from the British Empire, and it remained as such, for practical purposes, until April 29, 1878, when Congress charged the U.S. Marine-Hospital Service with enforcement of public health regulations promulgated by the U.S. secretary of treasury.</p><p local-id="A6424C_65">Where is quarantine going today? Is it a medieval tool that has outlasted its usefulness, or has it been transformed into the most powerful prescription for highly communicable and highly lethal disease? Perhaps more importantly, playing the instrument of quarantine requires a master cadre of professionals who have played the quarantine tune and know how to lead those who must adhere to its practices. Much like the Pied Piper who magically rid the rats from their hiding places and saved a German village from the plague, the art of quarantine requires the right blend of skills, resources, and public support for any public health Pied Piper to succeed. You will soon learn of many ways that quarantine has gone wrong, but you will also learn of the magic that makes it work.</p></div></front><div local-id="A6424C_66" type="chapter"><page-start number="pgxviii"></page-start><page-start number="pg1"></page-start><content-metadata><label>CHAPTER ONE</label><title>The Quarantine Grab Bag</title></content-metadata><p local-id="A6424C_67">The modern notion of quarantine dates back to 1917, when Dr. Haven Emerson, one of the great public health reformers of the twentieth century and the grandnephew of Ralph Waldo Emerson, defined it as the limitation of freedom of movement of those suspected of exposure to a communicable disease for the incubation period of the disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1281"><display-text><sup>1</sup></display-text></ref> Emerson distinguished quarantine from the concept of isolation, the latter referring to those confirmed as having a communicable disease who are separated from susceptible persons.</p><p local-id="A6424C_68">These old definitions, while still useful, fail to incorporate the grab bag of newer quarantine concepts such as “directly observed treatment,” self-quarantine, disease transmission dynamics, the “healthy carrier” paradigm, and the economic consequences of long-term confinement for the poor. For example, the concept of isolation was dramatically altered in the 1950s when it was decided tuberculosis patients could avoid confinement if they could be directly observed taking their medications.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1283"><display-text><sup>2</sup></display-text></ref> Similarly, allowing self-quarantine of individuals without supervision is perfectly reasonable for diseases that are relatively nonlethal and not easily transmitted and can be easily managed from a distance via phone, fax, internet guidance, or telemedicine.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1285"><display-text><sup>3</sup></display-text></ref> But what if hospitalization is required? Hospitals must be capable of handling surge capacities in an emergency and must have access to emergency hospital systems that are transportable and properly staffed at the perimeter of the hot zones. To be effective, quarantine systems must consider the complete range of disease transmission dynamics and must be supported by (1) public policy, (2) public resources, and (3) public support. Quarantine only works if these three key elements are present. These principles are of critical importance when quarantine is applied to low-income persons incapable of financially weathering the consequences of unemployment during a pandemic. Unless quarantine is humanized in its applications, public health officials can expect significant resistance to traditional forms of confinement.</p><p local-id="A6424C_69"><page-start number="pg2"></page-start>Since 2006, mindful of the pejorative meanings of nineteenth-century uses of quarantine, some public health officials have referred to “nonpharmaceutical interventions” as a more acceptable means of dressing up quarantine concepts in new clothing.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1287"><display-text><sup>4</sup></display-text></ref> Nonpharmaceutical interventions is a much broader concept than quarantine, since such interventions include voluntary and involuntary restrictions on movement and social gatherings of the general population as well as government-imposed public hygiene and business closure measures.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1289"><display-text><sup>5</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_70">What makes quarantine an intellectually challenging assignment for a public health professional is that all of the major elements of the quarantine grab bag—including policies that impose hospital or home isolation; close ports, airports, and border crossings; and require social distancing and respiratory protection—all depend upon three key variables: public trust, transparent government decision making, and the ability to adopt triage principles when resources and staff become scarce. These issues are discussed in the last chapter of this book.</p><section local-id="A6424C_71"><head>Quarantine as the Ultimate Weapon</head><p local-id="A6424C_72">Outdated concepts of quarantine are not the only reason for the sluggish acceptance of distancing strategies as a viable tool in twenty-first-century epidemic response plans. Our inability to respond to epidemics also reflects another major development: our increasing vulnerability to novel pathogens. In 2001, Mark Woolhouse and his colleagues identified 1,415 infectious organisms that are pathogenic for humans. A total of 61 percent of these pathogens are zoonotic in origin, underscoring the degree to which human disease is influenced by our ever-increasing contact with other species.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1291"><display-text><sup>6</sup></display-text></ref> This ever-expanding list of communicable diseases impacting modern society also raises the fundamental question of what level of public health threat merits the imposition of hospital, home, neighborhood, or citywide quarantine. As a result of limited public policy debates, we still live with quarantine principles that share much in common with the expulsion rites of primitive societies even as the science of disease transmission and prevention has evolved.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1293"><display-text><sup>7</sup></display-text></ref> We have raised our understanding of appropriate treatments for communicable disease far beyond those available in the colonial era, yet we still operate with an all-too-simple definition of how quarantine should be applied.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1295"><display-text><sup>8</sup></display-text></ref> Since the beginning of the twentieth century, quarantine has been transformed from a tool to inspect and detain ships engaged in maritime commerce to one primarily applied in a hospital setting. Yet, few epidemics of the past were ever completely managed in a hospital. Indeed, hospital resources are always insufficient to cope with large-scale epidemics.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1297"><display-text><sup>9</sup></display-text></ref> It is well-nigh time to thoroughly review non-hospital-based quarantine in light of our woefully inadequate expertise in handling large-scale epidemics. Few large-scale quarantine events have ever had all of the necessary ingredients to be effective. In short, we have only a few shining examples in American history where a <page-start number="pg3"></page-start>scientific and humanitarian approach to quarantine has been successful in nonhospital settings.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1299"><display-text><sup>10</sup></display-text></ref> Like playing a violin, practice determines success, and we live in a society where few are practicing for the arrival of a large-scale epidemic. It is hoped that the historical quarantine practices this book documents will illustrate how large-scale events can be effective and explain how some of the brilliant quarantine masters of the past succeeded—or at least minimized ineffective strategies. Just remember the Ebola crisis of 2014 if you need a recent example of a faulty response to a relatively small-scale epidemic. If the Ebola crisis was a wake-up call for action—with barely any impact on the American public health system—the COVID-19 pandemic is a full-scale battle cry for the survival of America’s hospitals, nursing homes, and the nation’s economy.</p><p local-id="A6424C_73">Why have quarantine practices been so poorly studied in a society so focused on scientific advances in the public health and medical fields? With only a few exceptions, the absence of large-scale epidemics in America during the period 1960–2003 has curtailed scientific interest in quarantine practice.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1301"><display-text><sup>11</sup></display-text></ref> Epidemics are the testing ground of new ideas and policies, and it is only events like the 2003 SARS epidemic, the 2014 Ebola crisis, and the 2020 COVID-19 pandemic that help crystallize revised approaches to quarantine. Quarantine, as one of the most extreme distancing strategies, should be reserved for the most lethal of all communicable pathogens.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_74"><head>Epidemic Response—Large-Scale Quarantine</head><p local-id="A6424C_75">The mere existence of isolation hospitals does not end the need for large-scale quarantine—they merely dampen the urgency for such strategies as long as cases of communicable disease can be identified and treated promptly. Desultory responses to an outbreak inevitably raise the resources required to quell the spread of disease and make it impossible to contain epidemics within isolation hospitals. Waiting months before responding to an epidemic inevitably increases the cost of detection, inspection, treatment, and quarantine as well as the needless sacrifice of lives.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1303"><display-text><sup>12</sup></display-text></ref> Successful containment strategies depend upon enabling laws, public health infrastructure, financial support, and the application of the latest science of public hygiene, social engineering, and “nudge” principles advocated by Cass Sunstein.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1305"><display-text><sup>13</sup></display-text></ref> As Sunstein has correctly pointed out, people can be encouraged or nudged to do the right thing and accept quarantine when they are offered the right incentives and choices.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_76"><head>Germs and Public Hygiene</head><p local-id="A6424C_77">Antibiotic drugs are only a recent invention dating back to the period prior to World War II.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1307"><display-text><sup>14</sup></display-text></ref> Previously, it was common practice to isolate individuals infected with contagious disease. However, improvements in the diagnosis of quarantinable disease followed by rapid discoveries of their etiology and <page-start number="pg4"></page-start>transmission characteristics made it possible to improve treatment and disinfection strategies and minimize the use of isolation practices.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1309"><display-text><sup>15</sup></display-text></ref> By 1893, when the U.S. Treasury Department declared cholera, smallpox, typhus fever, yellow fever, plague, and leprosy as quarantinable diseases, the etiology of half of these diseases was known.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1311"><display-text><sup>16</sup></display-text></ref> By World War I, these diseases were identified as either bacterial or viral in nature and whether they were vector-borne (e.g., plague is transmitted via the rat flea, yellow fever via the <i>Aedes aegypti</i> mosquito, and typhus via lice). These developments dramatically changed the use of quarantine. Rather than past efforts that focused on miasmas and overemphasized broad-brush sanitation of vessels due to a misconception that filth was a causative factor of disease, the U.S. Public Health Service (USPHS) developed disease-specific isolation and disinfection strategies.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1313"><display-text><sup>17</sup></display-text></ref> These dramatic improvements in public hygiene and vector-based quarantines raised public trust in public health and facilitated expanded legal authority for the USPHS in its fight against epidemic disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1315"><display-text><sup>18</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_78">In 1893, when Congress authorized the federal government to assume control of maritime quarantine, it set in motion the nation’s first systematic and scientific approach to large-scale disease control. Knowing the critical role vectors such as the rat flea play in the spread of bubonic plague completely transformed traditional quarantine. Rather than focusing on ship sanitation without a specific disease in mind, by 1910, the revised quarantine regulations of the USPHS identified specific fumigation strategies to rid vessels of rats and rat fleas. Quarantine could now focus on isolation and destruction of disease vectors rather than isolating the passengers and crew—unless there was evidence to the contrary. The USPHS invested millions of dollars to improve its fumigation methods to minimize damage to ships and their cargo and maximize the extermination of rats and rat fleas. Their fumigation techniques were so successful that in World War II the Nazis adopted the use of these same chemicals for the horrific killing of Jews in gas chambers.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1317"><display-text><sup>19</sup></display-text></ref> Zyklon B, the fumigant of choice for post–World War I American maritime quarantine stations and for Nazi gas chambers, remains one of the most lethal fumigants ever created. Its legacy is now forever more tainted by its misuse, not only in Germany but by careless applications during vessel disinfection.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1319"><display-text><sup>20</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_79">Advances in public hygiene have not all led to unintended and sinister applications. Improvements in our standard of living have led to better nutrition and hygiene habits, which in turn have facilitated a greater public receptivity to self-actuated quarantine strategies that rely on our own distancing skills and hygiene practices to enhance our well-being.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1321"><display-text><sup>21</sup></display-text></ref> Changes in cultural practices over the last one hundred years have also dramatically changed our exposure to disease. For example, spitting in restaurants or on public streets was prohibited in many American cities after it was learned expectorate could harbor the causative agent of tuberculosis.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1323"><display-text><sup>22</sup></display-text></ref> Similarly, the requirement <page-start number="pg5"></page-start>that food service workers adhere to handwashing became a public health priority after it was learned that typhoid could be conveyed as a food-borne illness.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1325"><display-text><sup>23</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_80">Personal hygiene, in so far as it establishes standards for limiting the spread of germs, is central to self-actuated quarantine, which can be defined as choosing to isolate yourself from society, your workplace, or social gatherings to minimize exposure to communicable disease. This includes handwashing, avoiding hugs and handshakes, avoiding or limiting contact in publicly shared spaces (e.g., avoiding doorknobs, bus and subway straps, and armrests, etc.), avoiding contact with exotic animals, and keeping outside the cough zone of others during an epidemic.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1327"><display-text><sup>24</sup></display-text></ref> Why are such practices important? The federal government neither has the resources nor capability to control your exposure to communicable disease. Individual responsibility for personal hygiene is the foundation for any healthy society.</p><p local-id="A6424C_81">Inevitably, disease control depends upon an informed and educated citizenry that understands what is in its own best interest to survive. Commonsense quarantine principles can be applied to limit disease exposure, <page-start number="pg6"></page-start>infection, transmission, and, under worst-case conditions, the epidemic spread of disease. These four levels have been described as the pathogen pyramid and provide a useful model for understanding where self-actuated quarantine begins and government-sponsored quarantine takes over (see <ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_5046"><display-text>figure 1.1</display-text></ref>).<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1329"><display-text><sup>25</sup></display-text></ref> To be effective, quarantine works best when undertaken at the bottom of the pyramid—when you make the effort to limit exposure to human pathogens. This, of course, implies you understand how disease is transmitted.</p><insert-here behavior="float" rid="A6424C_5046"></insert-here></section><section local-id="A6424C_82"><head>Overcoming Quarantine Baggage</head><p local-id="A6424C_83">Despite its intended use as a tool to segregate those with communicable disease from the rest of society, quarantine’s unwritten purpose often went beyond public health—influenced by concepts of class, ethnicity, and entitlement dictated by the ruling class.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1331"><display-text><sup>26</sup></display-text></ref> Colonial quarantine practice was rooted in a paternalistic approach to public health that, in most cases, quarantined the sick with little input from those affected.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1333"><display-text><sup>27</sup></display-text></ref> When islands were found to be too small to contend with large-scale epidemics, neighborhood quarantines were used against the poor, disenfranchised ethnic groups, and other undesirable classes of immigrants. Forced removal or neighborhood confinement fell out of favor after the colonial era when it became acceptable to permit home quarantine. The unintended impacts of various types of quarantine have left cultural scars on its legacy, which must be attended to before scientific approaches to quarantine can achieve maturity. There is simply too much distrust of governmental “top-down” approaches to quarantine to be effective without expiating the sins of the past. To resuscitate evidence-based quarantine, we also need to understand its value and public health benefits if we are to successfully overcome its historical baggage. Four pieces of that intellectual baggage are most salient: (1) its past focus on coercive means of implementing large-scale quarantines, (2) culturally insensitive approaches to quarantine of minorities and ethnic groups, (3) disease reporting as a form of ratting out minorities, and (4) gaps in the effective integration of the media into the organization and communication of quarantine strategies.</p><section local-id="A6424C_84"><head>Noncoercive Confinements</head><p local-id="A6424C_85">The public health profession believes quarantine should always be used as a last resort for species preservation.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1335"><display-text><sup>28</sup></display-text></ref> It has long been applied to lethal communicable diseases to isolate the individual from the rest of society—not for their own good so much as for that of the broader society. The common cold is highly communicable but far from lethal and <page-start number="pg7"></page-start>therefore has never met the test for quarantine—even though having a cold might get you a note to stay home from work or school. Government intervention is implied by the use of the term “quarantine,” and it is axiomatic that self-quarantine as in the case of the common cold would not be acceptable for lethal communicable diseases. The litmus test of whether self-quarantine could take the place of government-imposed quarantine depends on whether this less restrictive means of isolation could achieve the same objective. Third-party supervision is implied by today’s quarantine laws with the presumption that force, or at least voluntary compliance with mandatory procedures, may be required to restrain infected individuals from spreading disease. Yet, time and again quarantines have failed when the authority to quarantine is imposed without consultation with the people most directly impacted—those suspected of exposure to lethal pathogens. The results have often been counterproductive: those forced to undergo quarantine experience an overwhelming desire to evade its clutches when personal freedom of movement, freedom of choice, and social contact with family and friends are violated.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1337"><display-text><sup>29</sup></display-text></ref> Americans have long had antiauthoritarian inclinations when forced into large-scale quarantine.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1339"><display-text><sup>30</sup></display-text></ref> Applying military or police powers to control epidemics, without the resources or public acceptance to do it properly, has often unwittingly spread diseases like smallpox and cholera into the hinterlands when their victims tried to escape.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1341"><display-text><sup>31</sup></display-text></ref> The lessons from Boston’s history are quite clear. Quarantine fiats carry a heavy price: they can fuel epidemics when such practices activate the “fight-or-flight” syndrome among infected victims.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_86"><head>Culturally Sensitive Isolation</head><p local-id="A6424C_87">The intellectual detritus of quarantine also includes misguided policies that applied force to confine smallpox patients on islands, comingling the infected and exposed populations in crowded pest houses,—a seventeenth-century term for communicable disease hospitals, neighborhood quarantines imposed based on class or ethnicity, or required ship sanitation for diseases that could not be transmitted through fomites. These past abuses or misuses have discouraged modern-day uses of quarantine even when ample evidence exists that it plays an important role in stopping disease transmission. Some of the ill effects of quarantine can be fixed by improving the decision-making process. For example, before quarantine is applied, public health officials should always select the most effective strategy that does the least harm to the patient. This approach is consistent with the nonbinding Siracusa principles issued by the United Nations Economic and Social Council.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1343"><display-text><sup>32</sup></display-text></ref> The Siracusa principles espouse certain inalienable rights of citizens to freedom of mobility: “Freedom from fear and want allowing everyone to enjoy his civil <page-start number="pg8"></page-start>and political rights, as well as his economic, social and cultural rights when a nation declares a public emergency such as a pandemic.”<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1345"><display-text><sup>33</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_88">Use of excessive force to confine or banish ethnic groups is not the only historical legacy of quarantine. Those who fell victim to ghastly communicable disease were often isolated from friends and family at a time when such connections were most needed. Modern epidemiological studies have shown that survival rates of socially isolated persons decrease with loss of social contact.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1347"><display-text><sup>34</sup></display-text></ref> Despite hundreds of years of experience with quarantine, we have made precious little progress in understanding the health impacts of short-term human isolation or of improving the care and treatment of individuals forced to undergo large-scale quarantine.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1349"><display-text><sup>35</sup></display-text></ref> If you need a recent example of this problem, the death of nearly fifty thousand people in American nursing homes during the first three months of the COVID-19 pandemic points to a failure to balance the need for emotional support systems with the tandem need to halt the spread of the virus.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1351"><display-text><sup>36</sup></display-text></ref> Similarly, there are few credible studies that have evaluated the efficacy of using various distancing strategies to those exposed or infected with a communicable disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1353"><display-text><sup>37</sup></display-text></ref></p></section><section local-id="A6424C_89"><head>Defanging Race-Based Surveillance</head><p local-id="A6424C_90">A third element of quarantine baggage is its long history of being tied to arbitrary and capricious disease surveillance and reporting laws that emerged in response to trade and migration-induced epidemics.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1355"><display-text><sup>38</sup></display-text></ref> For example, time and again foreign vessels entered Boston Harbor without paying heed to its quarantine and inspection requirements. In 1717, the Massachusetts General Court, the colony’s legislative body, required commanders to check in with the military outpost on Castle Island in Boston Harbor before entering the port. Commanders were ordered to report disease on board under penalty of significant fines or even imprisonment.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1357"><display-text><sup>39</sup></display-text></ref> If the Holy Grail was to be found, it rested on their honesty and civic-mindedness. After numerous incidents of falsely reported “clean bills of health,” many colonies required a vessel inspection by either the island keeper or a physician to validate the commander’s sanguine assessment of passenger health. To the extent commanders without medical degrees could vouch for the health of their passengers and crew, this system worked relatively well for several hundred years.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1359"><display-text><sup>40</sup></display-text></ref> However, today we know some diseases are communicated by healthy carriers with no clinical signs of disease or by individuals with subclinical but contagious infections.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1361"><display-text><sup>41</sup></display-text></ref> Such nuances were not known prior to the twentieth century and certainly explain why even the most perfect colonial quarantine system was challenged to contain an outbreak when its disease surveillance system rested on the functional equivalent of quicksand. Occasionally, deadly pathogens slipped <page-start number="pg9"></page-start>through under the island keeper’s gaze simply because the passengers looked well.</p><p local-id="A6424C_91">Surveillance became more reliable in the nineteenth century when physicians were ordered to take an active role in disease assessments. Yet, physicians in private practice argued they were not the gatekeepers of American port cities and resisted disease reporting laws.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1363"><display-text><sup>42</sup></display-text></ref> Despite their protestations, they clearly had a greater understanding of disease symptomology than the average citizen and were growing in professional stature as medical societies took root in the young republic.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1365"><display-text><sup>43</sup></display-text></ref> By 1919, every state and territory required physicians to report specified communicable diseases.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1367"><display-text><sup>44</sup></display-text></ref> Yet, tagging physicians with responsibility for disease reporting did not eliminate arbitrary, and in many cases discriminatory, reporting of quarantinable diseases that targeted the most impoverished immigrant classes in urban America. Disease reporting has been rightly declared one of the great public health achievements of the nineteenth century. Yet, few historians have dared question the adverse impacts this reporting system has had on the abusive quarantine practices imposed on minorities. Certainly, disease reporting revolutionized modern responses to epidemics. For example, by the end of the nineteenth century, the battlefield for disease surveillance shifted from the doctor’s office to the public school system when Samuel Durgin, chairman of the Boston’s Board of Public Health, was shocked to find thousands of sick children—the sons and daughters of immigrants and the city’s minority classes—when he ordered public schools inspected in 1894.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1369"><display-text><sup>45</sup></display-text></ref> While children were rightfully tagged as the superspreaders of disease, these scientific discoveries led to increased government authority over the inspection, testing, and reporting of quarantinable diseases, which in turn validated the need for quarantine. To the extent that disease surveillance systems target minorities and function as a form of ratting out the poor and disenfranchised elements of society, government-sanctioned quarantine measures are tarnished as dictatorial or paternalistic measures. In the last chapter, we discuss alternatives to traditional reporting practices that avoid “ratting-out” practices of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_92"><head>Pitfalls of Freedom of the Press</head><p local-id="A6424C_93">Last but not least, quarantine has suffered from its coverage in the media, which has often influenced the success or failure of quarantine. Colonial newspapers were often responsible for inciting mass panic when reported stories claimed no cases existed or, even worse, that the last case had been quarantined when the reality was far different.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1371"><display-text><sup>46</sup></display-text></ref> It was proverbial that epidemics only happened in some distant land—not in the newspaper’s home city. Business interests were major customers of colonial and postcolonial newspapers, and it was not in their best interest to throw “gasoline on the <page-start number="pg10"></page-start>fire” and frighten shipping and commercial activities away from their home port. For better or worse, the media has always played a central role in spreading fear. On the positive side, newspapers have frequently given warning of emerging disease, enabling individuals to plan for an evacuation. For example, in 1764, thousands of colonists were warned to get out of Boston as fast as possible before smallpox reached epidemic proportions. On the negative side, not everyone could afford to leave their business behind when the economic consequences of not working meant living without financial aid or assurances of a seamless reintegration back into the work world.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1373"><display-text><sup>47</sup></display-text></ref> Without financial support, quarantine evasion and disease transmission among the cash strapped were much greater. This is a lesson that has far greater policy implications today than in eighteenth-century colonial America. Today, with an estimated 24 percent of all American families living within 200 percent of the poverty level, quarantines that fail to put food and money on their table when they are out of work (think rent, utilities, and other fixed costs of living in America) are sending a deadly message.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1375"><display-text><sup>48</sup></display-text></ref> Concerns with COVID-19 have struck the economy like no other time in recent American history, revealing the fiscal consequences of a poorly financed public health system incapable of responding to a pandemic in a timely manner.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1377"><display-text><sup>49</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_94">The freedom to report on epidemics comes with some important moral and legal obligations that remain largely unresolved even today.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1379"><display-text><sup>50</sup></display-text></ref> The media’s obligation to work under government supervision in the interest of a unified voice to the people remains one of the impediments to the successful use of modern quarantine. In an age where “government bashing” has become a popular media pundit sport, the public is often at a loss as to whom to trust. In fairness to the media, revisionist government positions on the risk of disease transmission for novel pathogens inevitably stoke fear in the public’s mind. For centuries, government officials faced with an actual or perceived epidemic have downplayed the communicability of the epidemic <i>de jour</i>. In their effort to dampen fear, they have often underestimated the communicability of novel pathogens or the wide range of ways they could be transmitted. Whom should we trust? On the one hand, the media makes its living by sensational stories that are intended to excite our innate fear of highly lethal gruesome diseases.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1381"><display-text><sup>51</sup></display-text></ref> On the other hand, the public is suspicious of the constant mission creep found in government declarations that “all is well” and that the disease in question is not very communicable. The media plays a critical role in checking government cover-ups or manipulation of the facts. However, in societies where the freedom of the press is given higher standing than stopping an epidemic, the challenges of controlling fear and panic remain vexing issues.</p></section></section></div><div local-id="A6424C_95" type="chapter"><page-start number="pg11"></page-start><content-metadata><label>CHAPTER TWO</label><title>Quarantine through the Generations: Five Stages of Practice</title></content-metadata><p local-id="A6424C_96">American quarantine practice has passed through five distinct stages in its evolution. These stages are not necessarily progressive and teleological steps toward a more scientific and humanitarian approach to quarantine. They represent generational stages that reflect the evolving political, social, scientific, and economic factors that have shaped quarantine practice. Indeed, the battle against epidemic disease has always been fought through both our emotional (e.g., fear and flight) and rational (e.g., scientific and analytical evaluation of communicable diseases) faculties, and for this reason many of the stages through which the concept of quarantine has evolved remain latent within our collective consciousness even today. What might be considered primitive approaches to quarantine, such as banishment or exclusion of certain classes of people deemed infected or “disease carriers,” may become popular when novel pathogens emerge that trigger fear of the unknown. Under this scenario, reasoned assessments of the risks of exposure may not be feasible, especially when limited evidence exists to make decisions. Regardless of whether quarantine was favorably or unfavorably perceived by each generation, it is one of the most important public health strategies available for highly communicable disease.</p><p local-id="A6424C_97">The five stages are (1) quarantines based on expulsion of the infected—or what may be called the use of the “quarantine net” to stop migration; (2) quarantines reliant on inspection and confinement until patients are free of disease; (3) quarantines of exclusion based on overseas surveillance systems <page-start number="pg12"></page-start>aimed at nipping disease transmission in the port of departure; (4) international quarantine strategies based on the premise of cooperative treaties among trading partner nations; and (5) quarantine strategies that enable internationally sponsored disease strike forces to quickly thwart disease transmission when the speed of transmission—not just exposure—drives the creation of pandemic events. The five stages represent overlapping and universal principles of quarantine practice that manifest to a greater or lesser degree depending upon the political, economic, and cultural values in each age. Throughout its nearly four hundred years of existence in America, quarantine has relied on the dueling principles of exclusion and acceptance of immigrants with one or the other achieving hegemony depending on the politics of the day. American quarantine evolved in tandem with the ever-increasing federal consolidation of power over public health. There is an ever-changing balance between efforts to consolidate quarantine powers at the federal level and the ongoing need for intergovernmental cooperation with states and local governments. Similarly, at the international level, quarantine can be understood within the context of an ever-changing balance between national biosecurity and the need for international cooperation in the battle against the common enemy of epidemic disease. These dynamic forces have shaped the use of quarantine consistent with the values of each age. With these caveats, American quarantine concepts have evolved through a series of anomalous events toward a more scientific and humanitarian approach.</p><section local-id="A6424C_98"><head>The Quarantine Net</head><p local-id="A6424C_99">In its earliest stage, quarantine functioned like a fishing net that captured incoming vessels to enable port physicians to identify and exclude sickly immigrants from landing on American soil. This strategy spanned the first one hundred years of settlement in Massachusetts, the colony that had the longest and most extensive use of exclusionary quarantine.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1384"><display-text><sup>1</sup></display-text></ref> Quarantine complemented laws that stipulated the wealth required of prospective residents and “warned out”—by excluding indigent or sickly newcomers—those who might pose a burden upon the community.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1386"><display-text><sup>2</sup></display-text></ref> Indeed Massachusetts went so far as to warn out those suffering from smallpox.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1388"><display-text><sup>3</sup></display-text></ref> Banishment of smallpox victims might seem cruel today, but such laws reflected the harsh realities of a highly contagious disease: as many as one-third of those infected died.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1390"><display-text><sup>4</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_100">With limited resources, and little emphasis placed on the public health of the immigrants, colonies set up island quarantine stations, desolate places of banishment devoid of hospitals. During the seventeenth century, nine of the thirteen colonies used offshore islands to quarantine vessels infected or suspected of contagious disease, and three (Maryland, <page-start number="pg13"></page-start>Virginia, Delaware) made no use of island quarantines—preferring to save money by detaining vessels in their port harbors over other alternatives. Much like primitive societies that exiled and stigmatized the impure to die a slow death in the netherworld, the colonial network of quarantine islands, spanning over eighteen hundred miles of coastline, were used to intercept and, in many cases, perform the last rites for immigrants before they ever set foot on American soil. Thousands of souls never made it to America—forced to live out their last days on quarantine islands managed by disciplinarian island keepers who were the functional equivalent of public health police with vast powers to inspect, detain, and fumigate people and their goods.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1392"><display-text><sup>5</sup></display-text></ref> The island keepers’ primary targets were those suffering from fevers, smallpox, typhus, and other so-called pestilential diseases. After six weeks of rolling breakers and tumultuous seas leaving English and Irish immigrants prostrate with sea sickness during their transatlantic passage, immigrants could still spend an equal number of days in quarantine until the military command, and later the island keeper, declared them dead or healthy enough to enter America. In the seventeenth century, there were no laws that required commanders to vouch for the health of their passengers or crew. Indeed, one of the lessons learned in colonial ports like Boston was that commanders had no vested interest in reporting the true state of health on board their vessels. The “good word” of commanders meant little to port physicians, when the survival of an entire city depended on an accurate assessment of the health of immigrant passengers. Similar disease reporting evasions have continued even to the present day, as many either can’t afford or would prefer not to seek medical treatment for mild infections that might stigmatize them as victims of a communicable disease.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_101"><head>Immigration and Inspection</head><p local-id="A6424C_102">With increasing migration to America, eighteenth-century American port cities began to accommodate the medical needs of the arriving passengers, building pest houses on offshore islands.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1394"><display-text><sup>6</sup></display-text></ref> A primary motivation for improved pest houses—the term of art for seventeenth-century hospitals—was the need to separate sickly residents from the rest of the population, and islands were the best means of doing so. At this stage quarantine did not stop the poor and sickly classes from entering America, but it did stop most from entering their port in a sickly condition. Rather than excluding immigrants from entering America, they were merely forced to remain on quarantine islands until they either died or recovered and no longer posed a threat to the residents of colonial port cities. Quarantine took on greater urgency when the colonies became the dumping ground for British convicts and the sickly poor. In 1717, the British Parliament passed legislation authorizing the <page-start number="pg14"></page-start>transport of prisoners to the American colonies. There was very little colonial governments could do to stop the influx of these disreputable members of society.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1396"><display-text><sup>7</sup></display-text></ref> Thousands of Irish, Scotts, and English came to America in lieu of serving out their jail terms in England. With the huge loss of life in colonial port cities from recurring epidemics, the need for migrant labor to support the commercial activities of the young colonies took precedence over exclusionary policies, and port physicians were hired to inspect incoming vessels to achieve those objectives. Pest houses were an investment in the care and support of immigrants who performed much of the essential work in the colonies.</p><p local-id="A6424C_103">A network of eleven quarantine islands was established near major ports along the entire eastern seaboard to evaluate the health of arriving immigrants.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1398"><display-text><sup>8</sup></display-text></ref> The locations chosen reflected the major ports of entry into colonial America but fell far short of providing a medical inspection system at dozens of smaller ports. While these islands were chosen without any thought of a coordinated intercolonial disease surveillance system, their common mission was to keep disease at bay with minimal consideration of the needs of the crew or passengers. Unlike today, the earliest island quarantine stations offered minimal shelter, failed to provide separate quarters for the sick and healthy, and expected the commander and his passengers to fend for themselves. Virtually, every major American port had a quarantine island that intercepted vessels prior to port entry.</p><p local-id="A6424C_104">Medical inspection was no mean challenge for eighteenth-century towns like Boston, which, in the space of fifty years prior to the American Revolution, inspected immigrants coming from over one hundred and thirty different nations around the world.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1400"><display-text><sup>9</sup></display-text></ref> It is estimated that seventy-five thousand immigrants and sailors were detained or quarantined in eighteenth-century Boston. With the massive influx of immigrants, the health of the nation depended upon the quarantine practices of each port. Before a vessel could reach port, it had to stop and report the existence of any quarantinable disease. All American colonies had quarantine regulations, and many were modeled on those adopted by the Massachusetts Bay Colony.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1402"><display-text><sup>10</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_105">Island keepers—not physicians—continued to be responsible for routine medical inspections throughout the eighteenth century with exceptions made when novel diseases emerged where the expert opinion of physicians were sought. Eventually, at the end of the eighteenth century, physicians were hired to conduct the work due to an increasing number of epidemics and a growing need for vessel inspections. As vessel inspections became a routine element of the quarantine net and epidemics became more common, Philadelphia and Boston hired physicians to conduct this work. It took more than a hundred years after the nation’s first quarantine before Boston’s Selectmen established an advisory role for physicians in 1779. A permanent full-time role requiring physicians to live on offshore islands took even <page-start number="pg15"></page-start>longer—that did not occur until 1832 when the city’s quarantine committee ordered a cottage built on Rainsford Island.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1404"><display-text><sup>11</sup></display-text></ref> The creation of this physician outpost coincided with the unprecedented influx of tens of thousands of Irish immigrants into Boston and triggered a large public investment in pest houses to contain epidemics on the offshore islands.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1406"><display-text><sup>12</sup></display-text></ref> Over 1.2 million were detained or quarantined in nineteenth-century Boston. In time, quarantine islands expanded to offer well-appointed hospitals designed with separate quarters for the sick and healthy and with farms, cemeteries, and separate living quarters for the island keeper and his charges.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1408"><display-text><sup>13</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_106">After America’s independence from Great Britain, immigration policy remained a state and local governmental function. With increased immigration, some states imposed head taxes and bonds to cover the burdens of caring for the indigent.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1410"><display-text><sup>14</sup></display-text></ref> State and municipal quarantine inspections were deployed in tandem with state-sponsored immigration policies until 1875 when the U.S. Supreme Court ruled immigration policy to be the domain of the federal government.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1412"><display-text><sup>15</sup></display-text></ref> By 1893, immigration policy was squarely in the control of Congress, and soon thereafter the U.S. Marine-Hospital Service began its takeover of state maritime quarantine programs, which it completed in 1921 when it took over these functions in eighty-five American port cities.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1414"><display-text><sup>16</sup></display-text></ref> This brought immigration and maritime quarantine functions into federal oversight at all American ports of entry. This was a revolutionary change in American immigration and quarantine policy, shifting both of these functions from state responsibilities—consistent with the U.S. Supreme Court’s decision that the federal government has exclusive jurisdiction over international and interstate commerce.</p><p local-id="A6424C_107">Since 1893, American immigration laws have had overlapping jurisdiction over communicable disease with explicit prohibitions on the entrance of foreigners with loathsome diseases—an official term applied to tuberculosis, syphilis, and leprosy.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1416"><display-text><sup>17</sup></display-text></ref> In contrast, American quarantine laws had a different purpose: to temporarily detain passengers (i.e., foreigners and American citizens) when infected or suspected of exposure to a limited number of quarantinable diseases, all of which were distinctly different from those regulated by the immigration service. The rational basis on which some diseases became a permanent bar to entrance while others merely triggered a short-term detention remains one of the legacies of the politicized classification system for communicable disease. Incurable and loathsome diseases triggered expulsion, whereas an individual infected with a curable communicable disease was detained in quarantine with the assumption that he or she would eventually have a lifetime immunity after they recovered. When the U.S. Public Health Service (USPHS) identified two communicable diseases but only one was curable, the curable disease could be quarantined, but the other called for expulsion. Congress never <page-start number="pg16"></page-start>intended quarantine to be a permanent bar to entrance into American ports. In contrast, U.S. immigration laws for loathsome diseases were purposely crafted to bar entry into American ports—or what might be called a quarantine of exclusion.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1418"><display-text><sup>18</sup></display-text></ref> The principle of quarantine has never been limited to a system of confinement. Excluding immigrants with loathsome disease represents one of many quarantine strategies used throughout the ages and perhaps one of the most controversial anti-immigrant strategies ever adopted in America. Yet, quarantines based on exclusion became far more sophisticated in the twentieth century when the United States switched the venue for medical inspections from the port of arrival to that of departure.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_108"><head>Coordinated Surveillance</head><p local-id="A6424C_109">By the early nineteenth century, seasonal medical inspections of vessels were imposed to avoid a rash of epidemics that coincided with an increasing trading relationship with Caribbean islands where yellow fever was endemic. In the third stage, the good word of the commander was replaced by an inspection by the port physician. Charges of government interference in commerce were heard in the press of the day, but these concerns were tempered by the overwhelming adverse impacts epidemics had on early American port cities. In the post–Revolutionary War era, surveillance systems and quarantines were generally managed by local governments with financial support provided by the state legislature.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1420"><display-text><sup>19</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_110">As the nation grew and became more complex, the “immigration and inspection” stage gradually expanded to a much broader system of coordinated surveillance as the central government acquired more legislative and regulatory authority over public health—especially with respect to quarantine.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1422"><display-text><sup>20</sup></display-text></ref> The first step toward a more coordinated surveillance system came with the expansion of the quarantine authorities vested in the U.S. Marine-Hospital Service (USMHS), forerunner of the USPHS. Rather than each state operating on its own recognizance, the USMHS initiated standard procedures for quarantine and disinfection and expected compliance or face a federal takeover. The second step toward a more coordinated surveillance system emerged when the USMHS created an early warning system to provide information on overseas epidemics and conduct passenger and vessel inspections before their departure for America.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1424"><display-text><sup>21</sup></display-text></ref> This was a radical departure from past practice and one of the most significant policy changes in protecting America from imported disease—shifting public health burdens from America’s quarantine stations to the health-care system of the immigrant’s home nation. A third step in the evolution of coordinated surveillance was the federal government’s massive expansion of vessel and passenger inspections entering American ports prior to World <page-start number="pg17"></page-start>War II. Over forty-six million passengers and crew were inspected at federally managed quarantine stations during that period.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1426"><display-text><sup>22</sup></display-text></ref> The commitment to disease prevention, including looking for disease at overseas ports before vessels departed for America, signaled the birth of international cooperation, which also led to a drastic decline in reported cases on board incoming vessels.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1428"><display-text><sup>23</sup></display-text></ref></p></section><section local-id="A6424C_111"><head>International Cooperation</head><p local-id="A6424C_112">The international cooperation that emerged after the USPHS established its worldwide empire of medical surveillance represents the fourth stage and would not have been possible without the trailblazing work of over twenty nations that adopted six major international quarantine and sanitary conventions between 1900 and 1926.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1430"><display-text><sup>24</sup></display-text></ref> These conventions created the foundation for collective public health decision making to prevent the spread of communicable diseases beyond national boundaries. While the United States rarely took part in international sanitary conventions during the nineteenth century, individual states collaborated in the pre–Civil War Era recognizing the need for a unified national strategy before international cooperation could ever occur.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1432"><display-text><sup>25</sup></display-text></ref> America was unable to participate in the development of international sanitary treaties until 1893 when Congress authorized the U.S. Treasury to take full control of the maritime quarantine system. International diplomacy required a unified strategy, and the United States was now positioned to negotiate international sanitary treaties and establish uniform nationwide quarantine practices. This stage saw the birth of American public health diplomacy and our increasing influence over sanitary treaties with our major trading partners—especially in the Western Hemisphere. The adoption of numerous international sanitary treaties prior to World War II standardized the control of quarantinable disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1434"><display-text><sup>26</sup></display-text></ref> These treaties, including the International Sanitary Conventions of 1903, 1912, and 1926, the Pan American Code of 1924, and the Sanitary Aerial Navigation Treaty of 1933, were some of the most important political achievements of the twentieth century and reflected the power that could be exerted against our bacterial and viral enemies when nations came together for a unified response to pandemics.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_113"><head>International Disease Strike Force and Self-Enabled Quarantine</head><p local-id="A6424C_114">The age of the airplane, beginning immediately after World War II, represents the fifth stage and has now forced nations to band together to collaborate on epidemic intelligence and disease prevention strategies like no other period in human history. While large-scale quarantine is generally less effective in halting the ever-mutating influenza viruses, it still has a role in numerous less contagious diseases for which medical prophylaxis options are not <page-start number="pg18"></page-start>available or ineffective, as discussed in later chapters. Telepathogenesis, I submit, represents a unique new development in disease transmission, facilitated by the rapid movement of infectious agents transported by our vastly expanded air transport system that relies on tightly packed seating arrangements with travel times far faster than the incubation periods of communicable diseases—or what is commonly considered the time between the moment someone is exposed to a pathogen and when he or she develops clinical symptoms of that disease. You can fly to anywhere in the world in less than twenty hours with only a slim chance that anyone will be found symptomatic of COVID-19 or any similar pandemic disease. Telepathogenic diseases, as I define it, rely on droplet or aerosol transmission of infectious agents facilitated by poorly engineered ventilation systems and highly congested transit systems, not to mention the unique role played by schoolchildren and other individuals who serve as disease superspreaders by virtue of their highly gregarious behavior, extended network of relationships, and unique abilities at spreading disease through coughing, singing, “spit talking,” and similar close contact behaviors. The very notion that social distancing will cure the ills caused by modern aerosol-borne epidemics is somewhat quixotic, when many of the principles espoused by government-sponsored social distancing concepts make many false assumptions concerning the appropriate distances to remain from other individuals and appropriate distances from someone who has just sneezed (at least six feet). “Social distancing” is a relatively new term of art for a very ancient practice. The premise of social distancing is that disease transmission can be curtailed by social behaviors and engineering designs that physically keep us at least six feet away from other people. While physical separation of people at home, work, and play can influence disease transmission, it is only one of the many factors that must be considered. For example, modern ventilation systems can be an important conduit for pathogen transmission even when people are separated by the so-called six-feet rule (more on that later). When an infected person exhales into a shared airspace and the air handling system functions to recirculate that air—in essence serving the role of a pathogen distribution system—social distancing is of limited value. Redesigning ventilation systems to exhaust shared airspace—rather than recirculating it—is the challenge we all face within congested working and living environments. Poorly designed ventilation systems in hospitals, hotels, the world of office cubicles, trains, planes, buses, subways, nursing homes, and other congregate living arrangements, where viral or bacterial particles can be transmitted through airborne means for extended periods, are examples of manmade techniques for efficiently spreading disease. Lost in the simplified messaging to the general public is a basic understanding of Stokes Law, which proves aerosol particles of less than five microns can stay airborne for longer periods of time than larger droplet discharges from someone who has just sneezed.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1436"><display-text><sup>27</sup></display-text></ref> Perhaps <page-start number="pg19"></page-start>more importantly, these smaller micron-sized particles are also the ones that are capable of reaching the lower respiratory tract where diseases like COVID-19 are capable of doing the most damage. Smaller micron-sized particles can be ejected farther and stay airborne longer than larger droplets.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1438"><display-text><sup>28</sup></display-text></ref> Understanding the physics of telepathogenic disease is critical to an effective and scientifically sound response to airborne communicable diseases.</p><p local-id="A6424C_115">We have entered an age where our own technological accomplishments have become the Achilles heel of our public health system. In the name of efficiency, we have created highly dense living, working, and entertainment environments that now facilitate the rapid transmission of disease. For example, the technological achievements of creating the New York subway system, high-rise elevators, escalators, and huge indoor sports arenas has enabled New York to make more efficient use of highly expensive real estate and become one of the most important entertainment and financial center in America. Yet, the price paid for these efficiencies in mobility and ever-smaller separation distances in public venues clearly influenced the number of people who died during the first three months of the COVID-19 pandemic. The consequences of our highly integrated world economy imply that few political leaders are likely to take dramatic countermeasures against epidemic outbreaks because, with limited epidemic response experience and no visible cases to be counted (after all who is counting all the asymptomatic cases that arrive daily into our airports), the fiscal consequences appear too great. The paradox of telepathogenic disease is that immediate action is required to contain the outbreak, but because few citizens display immediate symptoms of disease or those symptoms are associated with other less lethal disease, quarantine and social distancing mandates are postponed until there is a public health crisis.</p><p local-id="A6424C_116">The good news is that a crisis triggers a public demand for action—including quarantine and other nonpharmaceutical countermeasures. The bad news is that quarantine when applied as a reactive response to a crisis, days and weeks after the importation of many asymptomatic cases, is like closing the barn door after the horse is already halfway across the next county. The key to the fifth stage of quarantine is that self-actuated measures relying on individuals sheltering in place and adhering to some level of social distancing are some of the only politically effective tools to halt the spread of highly communicable diseases in America. The resources that would be required for the federal government or even any of the state governments to impose large-scale mandatory quarantine upon entire cities or states is simply not feasible. While self-actuated quarantines coupled with health conscious social distancing must rely on the common sense of each citizen to look out for their own health, such behavior can only last as long as food, shelter, and emotional support systems remain intact. In the fifth stage, unlike any other stage, individuals depend on logistical systems to provide food and other essential goods, and these services <page-start number="pg20"></page-start>require money and ultimately the fiscal support of federal or state governments to subsidize their needs and ensure the principles of self-quarantine can be practiced without the fear of death by other causes (e.g., starvation, freezing, or clinical depression leading to suicide or other self-destroying habits).</p><p local-id="A6424C_117">The unwieldy size of our social, political, and economic systems—and their inability to move quickly—requires individual adherence to self-quarantine practices for timely epidemic countermeasures to be achieved. Yet, this by itself is not enough; a complementary element of today’s quarantine principles depends on a new form of international collaboration not previously practiced under past international health treaties. Rather than mere cooperation, we need coordination and unified efforts that transcend borders and politics based on the principle of protecting the human race as a whole.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1440"><display-text><sup>29</sup></display-text></ref> The best and brightest epidemic response teams must now be deployed to the site of emerging epidemics anywhere in the world to identify the foci of infection and to deploy medical prophylaxis strategies in coordination with the ring quarantine strategy.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1442"><display-text><sup>30</sup></display-text></ref> This coordinated approach to disease etiology and transmission is already emerging in the world’s scientific community but has not been endorsed in the arena of epidemic response teams sanctioned under the International Health Regulations of the World Health Organization (WHO). For it to be realized, we will need a radical reformulation of the way the WHO operates so that nationalist interests are secondary to those of the world as a whole. This is no small challenge, but it is clear that COVID-19 and SARS have both revealed the vulnerabilities of adopting nationalist disease control strategies in a highly interconnected world. The same level of WHO effort that eliminated smallpox in the 1970s now needs to focus on developing the political support for international epidemic response teams that can quickly be sent to ground zero of an outbreak and impose ring quarantine to keep the infected right where they reside whether that be in a building, neighborhood, city, or nation. Ring quarantine is especially relevant during the incipient phase of any disease outbreak, especially if a rapid international response can dramatically reduce—if not halt—disease transmission. Fast-moving epidemics like the Spanish flu were once thought to be too contagious to control through quarantine—let alone ring quarantine at ground zero.</p><p local-id="A6424C_118">Yet recently, epidemic response strategists have modeled the potential value of home quarantine as a means to control the highly communicable novel influenza virus and concluded “household quarantine is potentially the most effective social distance measure, but only if compliance with the policy is good.”<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1444"><display-text><sup>31</sup></display-text></ref> This finding supports the value of decentralized self-actuated strategies that do not rely on direct top-down enforcement of quarantine. There are simply not enough federal or state resources to apply traditional quarantine given the immense barriers posed by a highly mobile and uber-networked society. This is not to suggest the federal government or even state governments do not play a critical role in <page-start number="pg21"></page-start>responding to disease outbreaks. Rather it is the type of role they assume—it should be that of the pied piper, not the dictator. The federal government, using its bully pulpit, must continue to raise public awareness of disease transmission issues and personal and public hygiene as well as use its fiscal resources to revitalize public health priorities to give greater emphasis to infectious disease research. It also points to public education as the key ingredient in controlling highly communicable diseases like influenza and COVID-19. Indeed it is the most powerful tool we have in our fight against epidemic diseases. Forget about expecting a vaccine on short notice for an emerging communicable disease. By the time an approved vaccine is available, the worst viral epidemics are usually over, and the only ones who care for the dead are the nearest relatives and, of course, the editors of the <i>Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report</i> (<i>MMWR</i>). This is not to say that a vaccine should not be pursued—it merely underscores the need to focus on the present crisis and apply sophisticated nonpharmaceutical strategies that can buy time for the eventual development of one or more vaccines.</p><p local-id="A6424C_119">Today, in a world of telepathogenic diseases, we are also far more dependent on international cooperation than ever before. There is an increasing need for nongovernmental quarantine strategies, as rural populations shift to urban centers worldwide and as ever-expanding humanitarian crises caused by war, famine, and vast migration of asylum seekers have created a perfect recipe for the spread of disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1446"><display-text><sup>32</sup></display-text></ref> The prime example of this emerging role is Doctors without Borders and the increasing public health consciousness of numerous billionaires who have taken on epidemic disease as a personal challenge. Bill and Melinda Gates are the examples of this new philanthropy transforming past governmental approaches to quarantine and disease surveillance.</p><p local-id="A6424C_120">International cooperation by itself is now no longer enough to stop a pandemic—especially when nationalist interests of keeping quiet about an incipient disease outbreak trump the “public good” of coordinated international response strategies based on a fast deployment strike force of public health professionals sent to ground zero of any given pandemic. Including self-actuated quarantine, private sector interventions, and more responsible advocacy roles for the mass media, other networking strategies are necessary to supplement government-imposed quarantine. The challenge we face is using the term “quarantine” to apply to a wide range of distancing, public hygiene, and disinfection strategies customized to the transmission dynamics of each disease. In our last chapter, we present a new approach to thinking about quarantining disease that reflects the realities of the twenty-first century. However, if we wish to avoid repeating the errors of the past, it is imperative we understand the origins of American quarantine and its public health, judicial, legislative, and regulatory foundations.</p></section></div><div local-id="A6424C_121" type="chapter"><page-start number="pg22"></page-start><content-metadata><label>CHAPTER THREE</label><title>Quarantine in the Colony</title></content-metadata><p local-id="A6424C_122">Plagues of the seventeenth century were as feared as any natural disaster of the age precisely because humans had no control over who would be tapped for death and who might escape unharmed. There were five seventeenth-century epidemics that triggered quarantine in Boston, including the West Indies yellow fever epidemic of 1647, the 1665 London plague, and Boston’s smallpox epidemics of 1677, 1689, and 1693.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1449"><display-text><sup>1</sup></display-text></ref> These are the earliest-known instances where quarantine was applied in the American colonies. Its widespread use was fueled by the political, religious, and economic values of that era and the trading partners of Boston merchants.</p><p local-id="A6424C_123">Seventeenth-century physicians knew little of the causes of contagious diseases. At the time Boston was settled in 1630, the germ theory of disease was still about two hundred and fifty years away. Modern medical scholars have emphasized that few communicable diseases were recognized prior to 1800. For example, prior to 1629, smallpox and measles were treated as one disease in London’s bills of mortality. Similarly, Boston’s physicians failed to distinguish between diphtheria and scarlet fever during the throat distemper epidemic of 1735 to 1740. The medical historian Ernest Caulfield, the leading scholar of this throat distemper epidemic, points out that eighteenth-century physicians misunderstood the nature of communicable diseases and were often responsible for its unintended transmission.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1451"><display-text><sup>2</sup></display-text></ref> Other contagious diseases were also confused, including yellow fever and malaria and typhoid and typhus.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1453"><display-text><sup>3</sup></display-text></ref> Terms such as distemper, malignant, and pestilential fevers and plague were often used to describe a wide range of highly lethal and contagious diseases simply because physicians were unable to distinguish the unique features of a disease. Yet, despite limited knowledge, physicians were able to identify many diseases based on symptomatology—even if many others remained indistinguishable. Contagious diseases were a special category <page-start number="pg23"></page-start>of concern to colonial governments; they signaled the need for quarantine to stop human-to-human transmission of diseases.</p><p local-id="A6424C_124">John Winthrop, the first governor of Massachusetts Bay Colony, had a rudimentary knowledge of the causes of various distempers yet felt perfectly comfortable in practicing preventive health measures without a physician. Disease was not the exclusive domain of physicians, when its root causes were perceived as attributable to lapses of morality, depravity, a dissolute lifestyle, improper dietary regime, or the inexorable laws of destiny.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1455"><display-text><sup>4</sup></display-text></ref> Physical health was taken as a sign of moral character and a gift of God.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1457"><display-text><sup>5</sup></display-text></ref> While these explanations were routinely used to explain public health disasters, Governor Winthrop knew they were of little practical value in responding to the horrors of an impending epidemic.</p><p local-id="A6424C_125">During an epidemic, the services of a physician—the vast majority of whom were either self-taught or learned their trade through apprenticeships—were generally sought as the last resort only after home remedies failed, escape from exposure was not possible, and fevers, vomiting, or uncontrolled pustular eruptions gripped one’s entire body. Perhaps the only thing worse than contracting the plague was to die at the hands of a physician. Patients could either be bled to death, poisoned with mercurial antidotes, or fed purgatives to trigger stomach convulsions until vomiting or excrement was ejected from the alimentary tract.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1459"><display-text><sup>6</sup></display-text></ref> Fear of the consequences of these medical treatments made quarantine an appealing solution, especially if a targeted class of undesirable persons could be singled out for exile from the community. The rich were almost always able to survive epidemics more effectively than others because they had the resources to flee town or isolate themselves for extended periods of time.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1461"><display-text><sup>7</sup></display-text></ref> In contrast, the poor could neither afford physicians nor the price of self-quarantine; survival not only forced them to visit the marketplace where contagious pathogens were most likely caught but also forced them to continue working to make ends meet.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1463"><display-text><sup>8</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_126">Seventeenth-century Bostonians, like those in other port cities, died at an alarming rate from a wide range of communicable diseases.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1465"><display-text><sup>9</sup></display-text></ref> Smallpox was the most devastating disease to strike, and it seemed to return, on average, on a twelve-year cycle coinciding with each new generation of children. An epidemic hit Boston in 1638, and subsequent epidemics struck in 1647, 1666, 1677, 1689, 1693, 1702, 1721, 1730, 1752, 1764, 1776, and 1792.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1467"><display-text><sup>10</sup></display-text></ref> With few exceptions, Bostonians could virtually set their watches in anticipation of the next event. Epidemics were devastating, since children were without immunity to smallpox and quarantine was an imperfect tool for protection. Historical records exist confirming an estimated 4,280 Bostonians died of smallpox in the seventeenth century.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1469"><display-text><sup>11</sup></display-text></ref> While this may seem like a small number, Boston was a village with about 4,200 people in 1677 when the worst smallpox epidemic occurred.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1471"><display-text><sup>12</sup></display-text></ref> In that year alone, 750 people died. The town grew from an estimated 150 persons in 1638 to 6,700 persons in 1700, with much of this <page-start number="pg24"></page-start>growth coming from the arrival of immigrants.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1473"><display-text><sup>13</sup></display-text></ref> Smallpox infected virtually everyone who lived in seventeenth-century Boston. Those who survived its gruesome disfiguring impacts gained a lifetime immunity and usually lived long enough to experience the epidemic cycle at least three times in their lives.</p><p local-id="A6424C_127">The pox was somewhat kinder to Bostonians in the eighteenth century; while there were 34,788 cases, only 2,416 died during seven major epidemics.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1475"><display-text><sup>14</sup></display-text></ref> These low death rates would not have been possible without the adoption of inoculation, the unprecedented quarantine of over thirty thousand Bostonians during the eighteenth century, and the decline in trade relations with England after the Revolutionary War.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1477"><display-text><sup>15</sup></display-text></ref> The value of quarantine was not merely a measure of deaths averted; it reinforced rigid bans preventing strangers and the poor from entering Puritan society.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1479"><display-text><sup>16</sup></display-text></ref> Quarantine protected the immunologically susceptible Bostonians from smallpox exposure and tended to lengthen the frequency of outbreaks compared with other colonial ports.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1481"><display-text><sup>17</sup></display-text></ref> Boston took quarantine more seriously than any other colonial port in the eighteenth century, issuing thirty quarantine orders against European, Caribbean, and sister colonies that lasted for over twenty-five years—a unique isolationist strategy that has until now never been discussed by medical historians.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1483"><display-text><sup>18</sup></display-text></ref> Smallpox quarantine orders accounted for nearly half of this twenty-five-year period, resulting in significant economic consequences for Boston merchants and their trading partners.</p><p local-id="A6424C_128">In response to each new epidemic, Governor Winthrop had only his English heritage to guide him. English strategies for controlling epidemics were very limited and focused on the isolation of households where infectious disease was found. Local governments in the Massachusetts Bay Colony were expected to manage epidemics with legislative support from the General Court. Even Boston, which was the largest port in seventeenth-century America, could barely afford the costs of responding to recurring epidemics, which in part explains why its chief elected officials, called selectmen, failed to allocate funds for quarantine or even public hospitals when such services were infrequently needed. Health was not a public commodity, rather it was a personal responsibility.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1485"><display-text><sup>19</sup></display-text></ref> Boston’s priorities were the removal of household wastes and the maintenance of the public way, yet these routine services were the responsibility of the individual abutters, not the town itself.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1487"><display-text><sup>20</sup></display-text></ref> Residents were also expected to fix their own sewers and care for their own families when sick.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1489"><display-text><sup>21</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_129">With virtually no effective medical remedies for communicable disease, physicians could only provide palliative care when epidemics struck.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1491"><display-text><sup>22</sup></display-text></ref> Poorly educated and relying on symptomatology to dispense medicines, physicians were trusted insofar as they confirmed the folk remedies citizens would otherwise seek on their own.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1493"><display-text><sup>23</sup></display-text></ref> Physicians were sought only when folk remedies failed and the patient had no other options.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1495"><display-text><sup>24</sup></display-text></ref> In an epidemic, every man, woman, and child had to fend for themselves.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1497"><display-text><sup>25</sup></display-text></ref> There were simply not enough physicians to meet public needs during a smallpox outbreak.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1499"><display-text><sup>26</sup></display-text></ref> In practice, managing the isolation of <page-start number="pg25"></page-start>smallpox-infected households, when quarantines were imposed by government fiat, required significant human effort to guard infected houses, feed the sick, and, in the winter, provide wood for heat. Typically, it might take several watchmen to guard a smallpox-infected family, and in some rare cases, dozens of watchmen were required to cover round-the-clock needs of large families. The inevitable shortage of guards meant quarantine barriers were porous, allowing contagious individuals room to roam about on their own—whether to accomplish essential functions or simply because they were “stir crazy.”<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1501"><display-text><sup>27</sup></display-text></ref> While Boston’s Selectmen provided guidance to halt the wayward behavior of gregarious townspeople, their public notices and orders were often ignored or never seen.</p><p local-id="A6424C_130">Far more popular were approaches keeping the infected from ever setting foot in the colonies. Virtually, every colony had its own quarantine island to keep the infected isolated from the rest of society.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1503"><display-text><sup>28</sup></display-text></ref> Islands were popular solutions to imported cases of smallpox but were like a bitter pill for the merchant class and frowned upon by the Privy Council, the King’s trade advisers. Little quarantine guidance was gleaned from the motherland, since such restrictions were a threat to unfettered commerce and, with few exceptions, was not supported by the British Parliament until 1710.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1505"><display-text><sup>29</sup></display-text></ref> As far as the Privy Council was concerned, public health and the lives of ordinary people were subordinate to the culture of commerce propagated by British merchants and shipping magnates.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1507"><display-text><sup>30</sup></display-text></ref> Yet, British mercantile policy had little influence on quarantine practice in Massachusetts.</p><section local-id="A6424C_131"><head>Religious Origins of American Quarantine</head><p local-id="A6424C_132">To understand the religious origins of American quarantine, it is first important to understand the political and social systems that enabled systems of confinement and exclusion that had strong support in the underlying isolationist values found in Puritan New England. Isolationist thinking found expression not only in the colony’s single-minded focus on Puritanism as the only religion; it was also expressed in the social and political policies of that era.</p><p local-id="A6424C_133">While quarantine was certainly not an American invention, the Massachusetts Bay Colony strongly influenced its modern development. The colonists’ emphasis on island quarantines in lieu of pest houses in the seventeenth century, the use of experimental strategies such as the eighteenth-century use of inoculation for control of smallpox, and the use of town meetings to assess public support for quarantine measures were more American in flavor than any previous British use of the practice that relied on orders from the King or his Privy Council.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1509"><display-text><sup>31</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_134">Yet, Bostonians also built a public health defense system that borrowed principles used by gated European cities. Boston, unlike most other American ports, was physically isolated from the mainland. The shores of the Shawmut Peninsula served as a natural barrier, and the gate at Boston <page-start number="pg26"></page-start>Neck, stretching about one hundred yards from the Charles River on the north to Boston Harbor to the south, controlled access to the entire town. The town was ideally situated to defend itself from any intruders, whether they be wild panthers, strangers, or infectious diseases. The town’s watchmen provided security throughout all hours of the day and week.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1511"><display-text><sup>32</sup></display-text></ref> When watchmen closed the Neck, the only points of entry were by sea, making it easy for them to inspect strangers and warn them away.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1513"><display-text><sup>33</sup></display-text></ref> Its unique geography made it simple to close the town to all potential intruders and contributed to its dominant role in the evolution of quarantine concepts in colonial America.</p><p local-id="A6424C_135">Boston’s founders, after all, were not initially keen on maintaining close relations with the mother country. The Puritans had fled to Massachusetts to establish their own separate religious utopia unfettered by the religious tenets of the Anglican Church.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1515"><display-text><sup>34</sup></display-text></ref> They were not seeking to create a British colony, even if they relied on their motherland for trade.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1517"><display-text><sup>35</sup></display-text></ref> Puritan life stressed the importance of the church and the unity of its parishioners in working harmoniously in a world dedicated to a godly life. Outside influences from agnostics, disbelievers, or members of other religious sects were not tolerated even though the church that was organized in 1630 was far from an orthodox institution. It took several years for these colonists to become acquainted and forge friendships and a common way of worship and, more importantly, a sense of unity within their community.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1519"><display-text><sup>36</sup></display-text></ref> Boston’s Puritan founders valued their isolation to avoid bickering with the Anglican Church on the validity of their beliefs and evade the oversight of the English Parliament. Charles Andrews, the eminent American historian, pointedly stated, “The Puritans in America wished to establish a state of their own which should be independent of alien control, not only of the principal company in England but also of the King and the English parliament.”<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1521"><display-text><sup>37</sup></display-text></ref> In reality, Puritans and Anglicans were more similar than different in their religious beliefs. Very little separated their views apart from the Puritan emphasis on the Bible as the revealed word of God; the Anglicans saw the Bible as the revealed word only on broad principles of the Christian religion.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1523"><display-text><sup>38</sup></display-text></ref> Yet, these differences, while minor compared with the Anglican Church’s schism with the Catholic Church, were sufficiently large in the Puritan’s mind to warrant the establishment of a separate colony, separate church, and separate community in the new world. Their withdrawal from the Anglican Church in pursuit of Winthrop’s vision of a shining “city upon the hill” created the conditions that fostered isolationist thinking that permeated the social and political institutions of seventeenth-century Boston.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1525"><display-text><sup>39</sup></display-text></ref> This isolationist mentality had and continues to exert spillover impacts on our immigration, public health, and infectious disease policies.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1527"><display-text><sup>40</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_136">Until 1686, the Massachusetts Bay Colony had its own charter, which gave the colonists a small quasi-independent church-state seemingly divorced from the influences of the Old World.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1529"><display-text><sup>41</sup></display-text></ref> The Puritan community had very <page-start number="pg27"></page-start>little tolerance for deviant religious practices or social behaviors. To some degree this attitude might be interpreted as a measure of self-protection used by the founders to maintain the integrity of their religious way of life.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1531"><display-text><sup>42</sup></display-text></ref> For example, as early as 1631, the colonists denied admission to their community except church members. Four years later, this restrictive residency standard was extended to limit the sale of property to church members or those likely to be received as members of the congregation.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1533"><display-text><sup>43</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_137">Quarantine against vessels, in this context, complemented policies of keeping out undesirable persons. Bostonians were painfully aware of the trials of living self-sufficiently, and for this reason strangers were not admitted unless they provided proof of their competence to contribute their fair share and gave bonds that held the town harmless from any and all damage associated with their entertainment.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1535"><display-text><sup>44</sup></display-text></ref> This principle, adopted by the General Court under Winthrop’s administration, took hold as early as May 17, 1637, limiting visitors to a three-week visit, but subsequent legislation passed in 1692 allowed visitors to stay up to three months.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1537"><display-text><sup>45</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_138">For seventeenth-century Bostonians, disease was also a manifestation of God’s displeasure with deviant behavior and a sign the congregation should renew its faith and atone for its sins. Spiritual ablutions were called for to cast off the poison of the heart that precipitated routine smallpox infections. For spiritual leaders like John Cotton, considered one of the most eminent clergyman of his age, disease was an opportunity to seek pardon from the Savior and be cleansed.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1539"><display-text><sup>46</sup></display-text></ref> While the focus was on self-purification, the threat of disease inevitably called attention to the dangers posed by strangers who brought the virus from overseas. In this context, quarantine was used as a fence against the incursion of infidels and disbelievers until they could be cured. Time spent in recovery offered an interlude from sin, where the purifying influences of prayer and repentance could draw out the poison and cleanse the soul.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1541"><display-text><sup>47</sup></display-text></ref> This was not a metaphoric perspective on Puritan public health strategies. Indeed seventeenth-century Puritan ministers like John Cotton believed epidemic diseases came directly from the hand of God and any attempt to intercede through quarantine or otherwise bordered on a defiant gesture against God almighty.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1543"><display-text><sup>48</sup></display-text></ref> Disease had a spiritual purpose, and one who sought to subvert such lessons by stopping destiny through self-quarantine might be viewed as one of little faith. Yet, quarantine, understood in its loosest sense as a confinement from worldly affairs, also served a useful purpose, purifying the body and soul of the infected, and for this reason its role was accepted.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1545"><display-text><sup>49</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_139">In contrast, Puritans practiced hands-off compassion for pox-infected immigrants landing in Boston. Those who arrived in port with contagious disease in the seventeenth century faced expulsion. Captain Samuel Legg’s quasi-incarceration on an offshore island during the summer of 1677 and the detention of British sailors on board <i>HMS Seahorse</i> in 1721 were two of the <page-start number="pg28"></page-start>most egregious examples of how quarantines were applied more severely to strangers than to the members of the Puritan congregation. To the extent communicable disease was imported, Puritans could hypocritically apply quarantine against foreigners even when they were conflicted over its application to kith and kin.</p><p local-id="A6424C_140">The Puritan mind was a rational one. They knew faith alone was not always enough to protect against the ravages of disease. Common sense dictated taking precautions. Their lessons were born out of survival and the fear of deadly pathogens. For the most part, Puritan leaders acted in the public interest, recognizing quarantine as a necessary tool to protect the community.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1547"><display-text><sup>50</sup></display-text></ref></p></section><section local-id="A6424C_141"><head>Trade Patterns and the Path of Disease</head><p local-id="A6424C_142">Restrictions on travel and trade existed in Boston since its earliest colonial days due to weather conditions on the Atlantic Ocean, the availability of goods to barter in trade, and disease and famine. Boston enjoyed limited but regular trade with England for almost ten years before it was founded in 1630.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1549"><display-text><sup>51</sup></display-text></ref> However, commerce was vulnerable to epidemics, and trade contracted with serious outbreaks of plague in English port cities during the years 1618, 1621, and 1629–1631. Again, during the period 1636–1637, London, Norwich, Sandwich, and many other English ports suspended commerce for months at a time.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1551"><display-text><sup>52</sup></display-text></ref> These voluntary contractions in maritime commerce set the stage for more draconian measures: governmental exclusions imposed upon infected ships coming from the motherland and elsewhere.</p><p local-id="A6424C_143">In March 1647, the Massachusetts General Court passed an order establishing a strict quarantine over all vessels coming from the West Indies. The order, the first of its kind in America, prohibited anyone from coming ashore or within four rods of anyone not otherwise connected to the vessel.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1553"><display-text><sup>53</sup></display-text></ref> Vessels could land on uninhabited islands but required license from the Governor’s Council. Every port town within the province was ordered to quarantine persons and goods on merchant vessels or offshore islands. The order came at a time when Boston felt the economic impact of reduced migration to New England.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1555"><display-text><sup>54</sup></display-text></ref> Emigrants had provided a ready market for colonial products, but as that market declined, Bostonians sought new trade outlets in the Caribbean islands and other ports where their goods could be bartered or sold. It certainly must have surprised Winthrop when the growth in trade resulted in the unintended importation of lethal diseases. The constant influx of English immigrants between 1630 and 1640 had provided predictable exposures to known diseases, of which the first Puritan settlers had relatively high immunities. Opening trade routes to the tropics was like opening Pandora’s Box—it exposed Boston merchants and <page-start number="pg29"></page-start>seamen to frightful fatal foreign fevers that failed to respond to the remedies of the day.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1557"><display-text><sup>55</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_144">Fear of a highly lethal epidemic prompted Governor Winthrop to enact landmark quarantine legislation when he learned six thousand had died from a pestilential fever in Barbados and an equal number had died on Christopher’s Island.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1559"><display-text><sup>56</sup></display-text></ref> Winthrop was one of the most respected members of the Massachusetts Bay Colony. Bred to the law, by eighteen he was a justice of the peace, and by forty-two he was chosen governor of the Massachusetts Bay Colony. He served as governor for eleven years and ruled with fairness, generosity, and a firm conviction in the principles of liberty.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1561"><display-text><sup>57</sup></display-text></ref> The colony had adopted a Code of Liberties, and Winthrop was instrumental in showing their congruity with those of England. Winthrop walked a fine line between keeping the colony from becoming an isolationist religious bastion of Puritanism and one that maintained strong trade relations with the outside world.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1563"><display-text><sup>58</sup></display-text></ref> Their challenge was maintaining sufficient trade with the outside world to meet their worldly needs and keeping as far away from the British Parliament’s meddling with their internal affairs. The commitment of establishing laws to create an ordered society also required their charitable execution. Judges and legislators had to be sensitive to the dangers posed by overly exacting and, in many cases, unprecedented laws. Winthrop was respected for his ability to weave charity into the discipline of government orders, which was never more needed than in 1647 when the threat of pestilence prompted measures to stop the influx of contaminated vessels—the very vessels that were essential to the economic survival of the colony. Punishing the ship’s captain with steep fines for a disease he brought to the colony would do nothing to stop the epidemic and might create an economic climate of distrust discouraging future merchants from doing business with the fledgling colony. Winthrop was fifty-nine years old when he issued the colony’s first quarantine order. No other colony, or for that matter, not even England, had ever chosen the path of maritime quarantine legislation to halt the spread of disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1565"><display-text><sup>59</sup></display-text></ref> Winthrop would die on March 26, 1649, less than two months before the order would be rescinded, but while he remained at the helm of government, he administered the law with sensitivity to the concerns of its victims—the sailors, passengers, and masters of the merchant vessels suspected of carrying a terrifying and highly lethal new disease. Unlike other Puritans of his age, Winthrop was willing to accept human frailties and recognized the “rule of hospitality to strangers,” which many of his peers were quick to dismiss if they did not see in them an overwhelming commitment to the Puritan faith.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1567"><display-text><sup>60</sup></display-text></ref> Several twentieth-century historians believe this may have been one of the first recorded yellow fever epidemics in the West Indies.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1569"><display-text><sup>61</sup></display-text></ref> Its effect upon Boston commerce was severe, as the Governor’s Council prohibited vessels from tying up at the town dock, forcing them to remain offshore.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1571"><display-text><sup>62</sup></display-text></ref> Whatever the disease, it killed its victims in <page-start number="pg30"></page-start>three days, though famine and drought in the West Indies contributed to this great mortality.</p><p local-id="A6424C_145">Novel pathogens have historically been a powerful stimulant for the application of quarantine, expulsion, and other draconian public health measures. Winthrop’s decision to impose quarantine was made on the basis of the best available local intelligence. The Governor’s Council never sought approval from parliament or from the Privy Council, the King’s royal advisers.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1573"><display-text><sup>63</sup></display-text></ref> After all, their charter granted them complete legislative autonomy, including control of maritime affairs.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1575"><display-text><sup>64</sup></display-text></ref> Their unilateral action was typical of early Puritan legislators who made timely responses to life-threatening conditions. A six-week transatlantic crossing followed by untimely deliberations by the King’s advisers and a subsequent six-week mail boat passage to Boston made it clear beyond doubt that epidemics should be dealt with locally in a timely and effective manner—an impossible task for the desultory decision making of the Privy Council.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1577"><display-text><sup>65</sup></display-text></ref> Despite its value to the Puritan community, in the years prior to the American Revolution, British merchants voiced displeasure for American quarantine just as they did for American evasion of British taxes on American trade.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1579"><display-text><sup>66</sup></display-text></ref></p></section><section local-id="A6424C_146"><head>Quarantine Practice Aligns with Isolationist Policies</head><p local-id="A6424C_147">The 1647 quarantine order blockaded West Indies shipping for two years, posing an enormous constraint on routine business activities. Captains of merchant vessels, known as masters or commanders, found it difficult to make a living. Inevitably, the fear of losing one’s livelihood eventually outweighed the risks of violating quarantine regulations, tempting several masters to fake their travel histories to gain access to town. The overwhelming desire to escape island detention was a strong motivation for masters to cover up their real ship manifests with a fabricated origin and destination for their passage. Such a ruse could only work if the crew and passengers colluded for mutually self-serving objectives, not a difficult decision compared to spending three weeks on a barren harbor island devoid of food or shelter. In one such ruse, the General Court discovered a man by the name of Dell conspired with three fishermen to convince Richard Davenport, captain of Castle Island, that they had not come from the West Indies.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1581"><display-text><sup>67</sup></display-text></ref> Davenport, a military man of distinction and a seasoned veteran of many battles against Native American tribes, chose a measured response to Dell’s deception. After an investigation, which determined the epidemic on Christopher’s Island had ceased some three months earlier than Dell’s arrival, Davenport released the men, but their cargo was held in quarantine.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1583"><display-text><sup>68</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_148">As Davenport was given little guidance to implement quarantine law at Castle Island, it is not surprising that enforcement was relatively lax. For example, the General Court had only broadly defined disease as plague or <page-start number="pg31"></page-start>“like grievous infectious disease.”<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1585"><display-text><sup>69</sup></display-text></ref> Once again, the infrequent and often novel nature of epidemics meant Boston Selectmen were left to their own wits to contain contagious disease outbreaks. If a passenger suffered from diarrhea, would that prompt Davenport to quarantine the vessel? A test case emerged two weeks later when another ship arrived in Boston Harbor with a prior nine-day transit through Barbados. This time Davenport inappropriately authorized the vessel to dock in Boston even though he found cases of dysentery on board—a condition he presumably thought to be of little risk to others. Four magistrates of the court inspected the vessel and countermanded his order, placing the vessel into a one-week quarantine on one of Boston’s harbor islands until they were satisfied there was no risk of infection.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1587"><display-text><sup>70</sup></display-text></ref> Medical opinions were never requested or considered despite or perhaps because of the dangers to public health.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1589"><display-text><sup>71</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_149">The 1647 maritime quarantine order, unprecedented in English history, was enabled by three major ideological developments that occurred in the prior decade. These were (1) the General Court’s excommunication of religious dissenters and warning out of undesirable visitors through travel restrictions to Boston, (2) the use of islands for military detentions as a tool of war, and (3) a growing political independence from the motherland that led colonial legislators to believe they had authority over maritime affairs despite parliamentary and Privy Council edicts to the contrary.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1591"><display-text><sup>72</sup></display-text></ref> The Massachusetts Bay Colony charter gave it many sovereign privileges, but the British Parliament took exception to this independent-minded behavior.</p><p local-id="A6424C_150">The General Court had become adept in the art of detaining religious dissenters in jail and forcing confessions to bring wayward souls back to the fold. Those who refused to adhere to Puritan tenets were banished, as was ably demonstrated by the excommunication of Anne Hutchinson in 1637.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1593"><display-text><sup>73</sup></display-text></ref> Such punishments illustrated the ease with which the General Court exercised severe reprimands—including prohibition of Quakers from entering Boston—for what today might be considered routine religious differences of opinion.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1595"><display-text><sup>74</sup></display-text></ref> Excommunication of dissidents was an extreme case of the more routine activity of warning out. Despite Winthrop’s belief in the moral obligation of Christians to care for strangers, the prevailing view was that strangers unable to pay their own way posed a threat to the economy and religious life of the community and should be excluded. Townspeople could ill afford to subsidize welfare cases when its own society was precariously surviving in the midst of ongoing battles with Native Americans and without support from the British Parliament. Under these circumstances, the colonists considered it a bitter pill to swallow when parliament began shipping them British prisoners—a unilateral action that only increased their preoccupation with warning out misfits, malcontents, and malingerers.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1597"><display-text><sup>75</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_151">A second development set the stage for Boston’s use of island quarantine. Two full years before the Court declared quarantine, the colony was <page-start number="pg32"></page-start>captivated by an ominous application of military detention on its eastern shores. French and English settlers had long fought for possession of the Maine coastline, since it was the closest land for English settlers arriving from the home country and offered numerous commercial advantages for both nations. During the winter of 1645, Boston merchants sent a vessel to trade along the coast of Maine only to have it kidnapped by Monsieur Charles de Menou D’Aulney, captain of Penobscot and a wily French adversary of the Puritans. Captain D’Aulney exiled the sailors of the merchant ship on a nearby island along the Maine coast. For ten cold winter days, these sailors were held in a small wigwam without fire or adequate clothing until D’Aulney agreed to release them. Forced to return to Boston in an old two-ton shallop with limited provisions, no clothes, no compass, or any weapons for protection, they barely made their way home. Their harrowing tale of detention on a coastal island left a lasting impression on Governor Winthrop and the magistrates of the General Court.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1599"><display-text><sup>76</sup></display-text></ref> An island exile had been used as a form of punishment against Boston’s men, and the government took notice.</p><p local-id="A6424C_152">Despite strong opposition from the merchant class, vessels were held on offshore islands, and passengers and crew were expected to fend for themselves—an indignity that stretched Governor Winthrop’s notions of Christian charity. This strategy was, on its surface, designed to separate the sick from the healthy, though its style of application carried clear signs of punishment. Victims were treated as impure of spirit as well as of body. Shocking as it may sound, it was expected survivors would fend for themselves largely because Boston officials professed no moral obligation to care for these strangers.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1601"><display-text><sup>77</sup></display-text></ref> Ministrations to those in such a condition were limited under Puritan mores to members of their own community. Survival of the fittest was the rule of the day. Contrary to some modern misconceptions that Puritans placed religious principles above all otherworldly values, under the duress of another epidemic, the Puritans practiced tough love, and pox-infected strangers were denied care on the mainland in the interest of protecting the public health. An insular society that survived on its own could ill afford such dangerous policies as allowing strangers to have access to local physicians.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1603"><display-text><sup>78</sup></display-text></ref> Quarantine was a blunt instrument of self-defense against the “spiritual disorders” of outsiders.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1605"><display-text><sup>79</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_153">The General Court would not adopt quarantine laws against their own community members until the eighteenth century, when smallpox outbreaks became a more pervasive threat to public health. Quarantine as applied in the seventeenth century is best understood as a facet of a highly rigid social code that exiled, tortured, isolated, and removed dissidents to achieve its objectives. The distinction between excommunication, restricted visitation rights for outsiders, limited access through Boston Neck (i.e., the gateway to Boston), and quarantine of people and goods revealed the <page-start number="pg33"></page-start>diversity of strategies aimed at protecting Puritans from the evils of the outside world. Diversity of religious beliefs was not a virtue. Indeed, it represented a frontal assault on the integrity and way of life of Boston’s founding fathers.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1607"><display-text><sup>80</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_154">Despite an avowed belief that each person should realize his or her abilities on earth through good works, Boston’s early settlers supported a broad underclass composed of blacks, Indians, Irish, and indentured Englishmen who performed manual labor and most of the colony’s dirty work. These social classes were not considered equals even when they were members of the Congregational Church. For example, the General Court required the Irish to register upon arrival in Boston with the intent to control their mobility, limit their full participation within society, and record their differences from the Puritans.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1609"><display-text><sup>81</sup></display-text></ref> The General Court supported the Puritans’ caste system by restraining secular activities to bend human behavior toward Christian values. Even though Winthrop sought a theocratic state where religious liberty was cherished and the community could lead a godly life, these liberties were narrowly cast, limited to creating a society that supported a Puritan way of life; therefore, other religious groups were not welcome, at least not prior to the charter reforms of 1686.</p><p local-id="A6424C_155">A society that fosters a caste culture establishes the social milieu that facilitates the application of divisive social policies in various other arenas as well. For example, the leading families in Boston kept American Indians as domestic servants.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1611"><display-text><sup>82</sup></display-text></ref> While Puritan families viewed such practices as compassionate acts designed to save the lives of Indian women and children who survived the bloody battles with the settlers, there was no question about the spiritual hierarchy that emerged. Africans shared a similar fate. The slave trade with West Indies brought hundreds of Africans to Boston prior to 1700, and these individuals were virtually all conscripted as domestic servants. In instances where Africans and American Indians were set free, of which there were twenty-six known in Boston, social policy still called for them to conduct street cleaning, remove waste, and perform other menial tasks as dictated by the town’s chief elected officials.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1613"><display-text><sup>83</sup></display-text></ref> Separating the working classes into groups in subordinate order to the Puritans created a social structure compatible with quarantine principles. Quarantine, in its broadest sense, was not applied as a tool to solve a medical problem per se; it strengthened established lines of social division and protected the social and religious values of the community. Its medical benefits were a fortuitous secondary value that reinforced the underlying caste system.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1615"><display-text><sup>84</sup></display-text></ref> Yet, quarantine could not be applied to commercial trade on a routine basis without disastrous economic consequences. Fortunately, for the merchant class and those whose livelihoods depended on trade, the Court repealed the quarantine order against the West Indies on May 2, 1649, after seeing “it hath pleased God to stay the sickness there.”<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1617"><display-text><sup>85</sup></display-text></ref></p></section><section local-id="A6424C_156"><head><page-start number="pg34"></page-start>Evading Plague Quarantine</head><p local-id="A6424C_157">Virtually, every communicable disease that struck Bostonians hitched its way into town on the backs of immigrants, merchants, their crew, or infected goods.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1619"><display-text><sup>86</sup></display-text></ref> Maritime trade determined the portfolio of diseases Bostonians could contract. For all of their independent-minded posturing, they had no economic incentives to limit British trade.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1621"><display-text><sup>87</sup></display-text></ref> Yet, when the General Court learned of the ravages of the plague in London, they realized unfettered trade must stop. Placing a quarantine order against their motherland was like severing the umbilical cord between the mother and child.</p><p local-id="A6424C_158">The panic in Boston was palpable. Despite their “otherworldly” values, Puritans increasingly relied upon British goods to support their lifestyle, and yet each and every vessel that arrived might carry the plague. The loss of commerce might cause suffering and affect the quality of life, but catching the plague was a virtual death sentence. No one knew how it was transmitted, thereby heightening anxiety for those who made their living through trade. More importantly, the plague’s catastrophic impact on European civilization in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries made it a disease of international concern because of its lethality and the speed with which it infected the European population.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1623"><display-text><sup>88</sup></display-text></ref> Over 50 percent of those who contracted the plague died.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1625"><display-text><sup>89</sup></display-text></ref> Its symptoms were gruesome: purplish buboes appeared on the body of victims at the site of lymph nodes, which would become engorged with pus as the body’s immune system tried to fight off the <i>Yersinia pestis</i> bacteria.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1627"><display-text><sup>90</sup></display-text></ref> Death was the expected outcome once the bloody buboes spread across the body—not even bloodletting could save souls at this late juncture.</p><p local-id="A6424C_159">Fearing the plague, on October 11, 1665, the General Court issued a warrant ordering Captain Roger Clapp, commander of Castle Island, to quarantine all vessels coming from England. An industrious fifty-four-year-old man Clapp and his six gunners were the town’s only quarantine staff responsible for holding germs at bay. Clapp had assumed command just two months earlier after Captain Richard Davenport was struck by a bolt of lightning while resting on Castle Island.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1629"><display-text><sup>91</sup></display-text></ref> Captain Clapp, although a deeply religious man of courteous and pleasant manner, had no particular interest in the health of passengers, even though he was now the final arbitrator of what constituted an infectious disease. His only duty was to stop vessels at Castle Island and collect the appropriate entry fee and fourteen pennies for the health fee before vessels entered Boston.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1631"><display-text><sup>92</sup></display-text></ref> If all went well during Captain Clapp’s inquiry to determine if any sickness might be aboard the vessel, quarantine would not be imposed, and the only potential exposure the townspeople faced might be exposure to sickly or asymptomatic immigrants who had been overlooked by the colony’s military personnel stationed on Castle Island, about two miles from the easterly end of Boston’s Long Wharf.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1633"><display-text><sup>93</sup></display-text></ref> <page-start number="pg35"></page-start>Erected in 1634 under the leadership of Governor Winthrop, it served as the town’s de facto quarantine station.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1635"><display-text><sup>94</sup></display-text></ref> With a military command managing quarantine and shipboard sanitation, it would be expected that infected passengers received little care, especially since the fort lacked nursing or medical staff, though the commander served as the de facto chaplain. The potential consequences of a motley crew of military men who had little appreciation of their role in monitoring the health of vessels can only be imagined. If physicians of the day were unable to distinguish between various types of diseases such as scarlet fever and diphtheria, how could these skills be expected from poorly paid soldiers?<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1637"><display-text><sup>95</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_160">Imposing a rigid quarantine against the motherland was an enormous risk for Governor Richard Bellingham to take, but it was one that soon paid dividends for the colony. His efforts to isolate Boston from European trade had the salutary effect of avoiding an American epidemic. While over sixty-eight thousand died from the London plague, the bacterium <i>Yersinia pestis</i> and the rat flea that transmitted this deadly disease never reached the shores of Massachusetts.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1639"><display-text><sup>96</sup></display-text></ref> Whether Boston’s success was a matter of dumb luck or its draconian quarantine measures, the specter of cataclysmic loss of life had been averted. No other American colony imposed, or indeed dared impose, a similar quarantine against the motherland, nor were there any reported cases in the American colonies.</p><p local-id="A6424C_161">The quarantine order was repealed on October 9, 1667, two years after its enactment. In reality, the order could have been rescinded in the summer of 1666, but Bostonians were so fearful of its wrath they did not accept secondhand accounts of the dissipation of the London epidemic. Merchants knew better than to contest the governor’s quarantine order, even though it would prove to be the longest one of the seventeenth century.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1641"><display-text><sup>97</sup></display-text></ref> Only a few isolated cases of plague occurred in London during subsequent years, but these few cases kept Bostonians on edge.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1643"><display-text><sup>98</sup></display-text></ref> Bellingham believed averting the plague was worth the sacrifice even if it meant some economic hardships. Why didn’t other colonies pursue similar quarantine strategies? In large part, the Massachusetts Bay Colony exercised a degree of autonomy from the English Parliament and the King’s Privy Council, which had no parallels in the other colonies.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1645"><display-text><sup>99</sup></display-text></ref> Their charter, authorized by King Charles on March 4, 1629, gave the colonists a great deal of authority over their own self-government as long as their local laws were consistent with those of England.</p><p local-id="A6424C_162">The London plague also underscored the importance of tracking epidemics in all port cities where Boston commerce was carried on. Bellingham and his assistants—assistants were the forerunners of the House of Representatives—were mindful of the limited value of information provided by arriving seamen and, consequently, relied on letters from merchants or diplomats reporting from foreign countries. Published reports were few and far between, in part because none of the American colonies published <page-start number="pg36"></page-start>newspapers in the seventeenth century. Only the diaries kept by a handful of literate merchants, ministers, and magistrates have left evidence of the devastating loss of life from epidemics.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1647"><display-text><sup>100</sup></display-text></ref> One might think that masters and commanders would be the logical source for epidemic intelligence, as they were obligated to provide reports of epidemics. Yet, they had little reason to report “an outbreak” if it might quarantine their ship. Moreover, smallpox, remittent fevers, and various fluxes were endemic in many of the ports visited by seventeenth-century Boston merchants, so reports of overseas epidemics (i.e., outlier outbreaks beyond the normal annual fatality rates) were the exception rather than the rule.</p><p local-id="A6424C_163">Despite the paucity of epidemic reports, documented cases invariably pointed to external maritime threats rather than from within Boston proper. Removing ships far enough out of port to satisfy the fears of Bostonians was the usual solution to seventeenth-century threats, even though such actions were undertaken with little formal legislative guidance. Starting on July 18, 1669, it became routine practice for Captain Clapp to deny harbor access to a ship with smallpox or other contagious disease or one coming from ports where such disease was present without the approval of the colony’s governor.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1649"><display-text><sup>101</sup></display-text></ref> Such quarantines, continued to be exclusionary in nature, with no humanitarian support to the passengers or crew, typical of responses to previous epidemics of the seventeenth century.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1651"><display-text><sup>102</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_164">The provincial government enforced numerous quarantines based on orders issued by the governor rather than permanent laws. One of the worst epidemics in American history occurred during the period 1677–1679, when over seven hundred Bostonians, or nearly 18 percent of the population, died from smallpox. The ghastly epidemic started on July 10, 1677, when a smallpox-infected vessel landed in Nantasket about eight miles from downtown Boston.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1653"><display-text><sup>103</sup></display-text></ref> Several Charlestown residents ventured on board, and within months thousands were sick. Bostonians had never experienced so many deaths, and by all counts the mortality rate was as severe as the London plague of 1665.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1655"><display-text><sup>104</sup></display-text></ref> Perhaps because of the relative laxity of the measures taken in July, the Governor’s Council took no chances with subsequent vessels entering the harbor. For example, when Captain Samuel Legg arrived in Boston Harbor later that year, the Governor’s Council ordered him to land his vessel on Deer Island and stay there for eight days before his passengers were released.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1657"><display-text><sup>105</sup></display-text></ref> In effect, the Council said, “Stay out until we’re satisfied you are not a risk.” To demonstrate the seriousness of this quarantine, it imposed a sixty-pound penalty on anyone violating their order.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1659"><display-text><sup>106</sup></display-text></ref> Since Deer Island was uninhabited, Captain Legg’s passengers fended for themselves until the order was lifted. More importantly, this incident revealed one of the flaws of this quarantine system; Bostonians did not consider the burdens of disease on board sickly vessels to be their responsibility, and Castle Island was never formally declared a hospital available for use by sickly immigrants—it was <page-start number="pg37"></page-start>only an inspection station for arriving vessels. Sick and healthy passengers were equally excluded until Clapp determined if they were sick. However, if there had only been one or two cases of disease on board, the outcome may have been far different for the passenger and crew, since Castle Island was ill suited to accommodate everyone on board. For this reason, Deer Island became the safest way to handle this public health crisis. Similar exclusionary quarantines occurred more than once in the seventeenth century with severe consequences to innocent passengers from the motherland.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1661"><display-text><sup>107</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_165">These callous exclusionary policies prompted the town’s selectmen to rethink maritime quarantine. On May 6, 1678, the selectmen instituted home isolation and ordered those who survived to clean their infected clothing at three designated common areas: the hill overlooking the Charlestown ferry, Fort Hill; one of the town’s highest promontories; and Boston Commons. There was only one condition. All clothing had to be removed and cleaned in the dead of night.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1663"><display-text><sup>108</sup></display-text></ref> Their intuitions about disease causation may have had little basis in evidence, but they proved remarkably accurate. Modern studies have shown smallpox can be transmitted through contact with recently infected clothing.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1665"><display-text><sup>109</sup></display-text></ref> Working off these experiences, for the next one hundred years, it was standard procedure to require smallpox patients to shed their old clothes before release from the town’s various pest houses. The selectmen’s strategy represented the first public effort to apply the principles of decontamination and disinfection to smallpox-infected individuals.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_166"><head>Founding of the British Customs Service</head><p local-id="A6424C_167">Control of communicable disease was complicated by seventeenth-century British navigation laws. The Navigation Act of 1651 required goods from the colonies and other dominions within the British Empire to be imported into England in English-owned and English-operated vessels.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1667"><display-text><sup>110</sup></display-text></ref> Likewise, it required imported goods to be carried in English vessels and to pass through English ports before arrival in America.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1669"><display-text><sup>111</sup></display-text></ref> It was also intended to subvert Boston’s trade with the Dutch in New York and ensure the Crown got its share of the revenues generated from colonial trade. Naturally, Bostonians strongly opposed the act, believing such laws could only be enacted by provincial governments along the eastern seaboard.</p><p local-id="A6424C_168">The navigation laws not only encouraged subversion of the British system for collecting taxes; they also had the unintended effect of making it more difficult to stop the entry of communicable disease into the colonies. Quarantine, to be effective, had to be uniformly enforced at the principal ports of entry into America. Without the resources for strict supervision over clandestine ports of entry, the colonies could only afford to monitor the health of vessels at its largest ports of trade. As a result smugglers reached New England through a wide range of small ports dotting the coastline. For pirates, <page-start number="pg38"></page-start>smugglers, and those seeking to subvert the customs laws of the British Crown, New England’s ports and unguarded islands were havens for contraband activity.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1671"><display-text><sup>112</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_169">With hundreds of natural harbors along the colonial coastline, it was impossible for one person to enforce the navigation laws of the British Empire. Yet, this is the strategy the British Treasury chose to implement. In 1678, Edward Randolph became Boston’s first customs collector. At the time of his appointment, Randolph, a forty-seven-year-old British government agent, was already a despised public figure in Puritan Boston. A monomaniac with an obsession with capturing every excise tax due to the Crown, Randolph had a knack for alienating virtually every New Englander he ever met.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1673"><display-text><sup>113</sup></display-text></ref> His efforts to squeeze every dollar of navigation taxes out of colonial merchants seemed to have a personal flavor. Before leaving England, he suffered financially even though he was employed in several apparently legitimate forms of employment, including working for the commissioner of the Navy buying timber and for the Duke of Richmond in Scotland in connection with some unsuccessful timber speculation. His work eventually brought him in touch with the inner circle of the Royal Court, a connection that led to an appointment as a glorified courier for the complainants of the Mason and Gorges heirs who laid claim to vast areas of the new world. His bossy investigatory style gained him few friends in New England. However, his confrontational tactics were thought useful to the Crown, and he was sent to New York to assume his duties, landing there on December 7, 1679.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1675"><display-text><sup>114</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_170">Randolph did more to annoy colonial merchants than any other British civil servant of the seventeenth century. His overzealous efforts to catch smuggling merchants and pirates along the New England coastline contributed to a break down in public health inspections of vessels in Boston Harbor. His activities heightened public distaste for English navigation laws and were a harbinger of the eventual annulment of the Massachusetts Bay Colony’s charter. Randolph took it as his personal mission to discipline the unruly colony on its flagrant violations of British trade laws.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1677"><display-text><sup>115</sup></display-text></ref> He vowed to bring the recalcitrant colony into compliance with these laws. His efforts, largely unsuccessful, underscored the inevitable link between commercial trade and the propagation of communicable disease. Unenforceable navigation laws subverted quarantine of infected vessels leading to little public awareness of the condition of such vessels.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1679"><display-text><sup>116</sup></display-text></ref> These cat-and-mouse customs enforcement policies became a routine challenge to Boston merchants during the last thirty years of the seventeenth and most of the eighteenth century. The British customs service did not prohibit quarantine legislation in seventeenth-century Massachusetts Bay Colony, but it did view such activities with suspicion, since they were undertaken without the sanction of British law.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1681"><display-text><sup>117</sup></display-text></ref> More importantly, the overzealous enforcement of the navigation laws undermined disease surveillance and encouraged disease transmission at smaller New England ports where Randolph was less apt to visit.</p></section><section local-id="A6424C_171"><head><page-start number="pg39"></page-start>Quarantine as a Public Health Tool</head><p local-id="A6424C_172">The grim reaper regularly cast the pox into the province with fatal consequences to its inhabitants.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1683"><display-text><sup>118</sup></display-text></ref> During the seventeenth century, thousands of Bostonians suffered from smallpox, with as many as 70 percent of the population infected, yet the fatality rate was generally less than 20 percent.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1685"><display-text><sup>119</sup></display-text></ref> The severity and frequency of these epidemics, coupled with the failure of routine methods of treatment, prompted the General Court to enact its first quarantine law in 1699, enabling selectmen to quarantine infected persons in separate houses. It also authorized two justices of the peace, working with the selectmen, to issue warrants directed to the sheriff, requiring them to place infected persons in convenient housing and stop any infected persons on board ships from coming ashore. Bostonians were facing a brave new world under the revised charter of 1686, where colonial laws no longer stood on their own authority but required approval from the Crown—even for matters affecting maritime affairs.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1687"><display-text><sup>120</sup></display-text></ref> This quarantine legislation was rejected by the Privy Council on October 22, 1700, since it was unaware of any similar legislation in any of His Majesty’s plantations, and the General Court offered no explanation for their privileged powers. The Privy Council was concerned these powers could be misused and noted that terms such as “contagions” or “epidemical” lent themselves to abuse and therefore were inimical to British trade.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1689"><display-text><sup>121</sup></display-text></ref> The legislation was taken up the following year and eventually passed on June 25, 1701, after the General Court eliminated references to the quarantine of cotton, wool, and other goods and dropped financial penalties against shipmasters—thereby gutting the enforcement of the new law.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1691"><display-text><sup>122</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_173">The 1701 legislation prohibited anyone with plague, smallpox, or pestilential or malignant fever to come ashore and who came from a port where disease prevailed. The justice of the peace was charged with supervising maritime quarantine and issuing warrants under the authority of the sheriff or constable.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1693"><display-text><sup>123</sup></display-text></ref> As trade expanded, so did deadly epidemics. An estimated four thousand people lived in Boston in 1675, but despite at least two intervening smallpox epidemics, the population grew to sixty-eight hundred in 1701, confined within less than one square mile area.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1695"><display-text><sup>124</sup></display-text></ref> Not surprisingly, this trade fueled higher density urban development that consumed virtually all the land not already dedicated to commercial, residential, or farming uses and made disease transmission a more pressing public health concern.</p><p local-id="A6424C_174">Despite heightened awareness of the devastation wrought by epidemics, there was little understanding of how to regulate the “fly-by-night” activities of masters and commanders. It was clearly cheaper for a commander to off-load smallpox-infected persons and let the town assume the cost of care. The 1701 legislation did not require vessels to be inspected or for the commander to check in with local authorities before docking at Boston piers. <page-start number="pg40"></page-start>They were not even required to have a copy of the provincial quarantine laws on board their vessel, nor were they briefed before arrival on their obligations to comply with these requirements. The law merely indicated the selectmen could isolate those with contagious diseases such as smallpox, plague, or pestilential fever in separate houses. It also allowed the justice of the peace to issue a warrant to impress housing for the sick and to restrain those with contagious diseases from coming ashore. How a justice of the peace could determine if someone was sick was not defined. Maritime control of disease assumed compliance with a hidden body of law that was less than perfect in its administration. With such limited guidance and enforcement, it is no wonder so little port security existed to control threats posed by sickly vessels.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1697"><display-text><sup>125</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_175">Despite its flaws, the law addressed both land and maritime quarantine and was one of the first in North America to establish permanent procedures to manage outbreaks of infectious disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1699"><display-text><sup>126</sup></display-text></ref> Enacted nine years before the first British quarantine legislation, this law suggests the Massachusetts Bay colonists were far more concerned with imported contagions than their English kith and kin.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1701"><display-text><sup>127</sup></display-text></ref> They were also more concerned with home isolation even though this was Boston’s secondary defense strategy. The primary strategy had long been to close the town’s gates at Boston Neck and ward off undesirable visitors unable or unwilling to pay their own way. This was easier said than done, as Boston Neck was constantly being eroded by the sea and damaged by illegal gravel mining activities.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1703"><display-text><sup>128</sup></display-text></ref> To reduce the ravages of the sea and improve this property, the selectmen leased out the neck lands to Bostonians willing to install fences, improve the road, and create a line of defense against enemies real or imagined. Those who had taken stones from the flats near the neck were requested to return them so that a fortification could be constructed.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1705"><display-text><sup>129</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_176">Eventually, the selectmen ordered a fence built across the narrowest stretch of the isthmus to limit access into Boston.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1707"><display-text><sup>130</sup></display-text></ref> Two watchmen were appointed to keep out undesirable persons and enforce the colony’s quarantine laws.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1709"><display-text><sup>131</sup></display-text></ref> Years later, the selectmen erected a substantial fort across the neck and closed the town at night—much like a medieval walled city.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1711"><display-text><sup>132</sup></display-text></ref> The fortification can clearly be seen on the 1722 Bonner map of the town of Boston.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1713"><display-text><sup>133</sup></display-text></ref> In observation of the Sabbath, they also restricted access every Saturday night for a twenty-four-hour period ending Sunday evening.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1715"><display-text><sup>134</sup></display-text></ref> The selectmen’s strict control over strangers entering town, its lockdown of public access in observance of the Sabbath, and its restriction of nighttime revelry established the physical infrastructure necessary to protect Boston from incursion of infidels. These exclusionary policies also supported a sophisticated disease control strategy the likes of which existed nowhere else in colonial America. In this sense, the town’s religious practices and xenophobic social policies were a natural complement to their quarantine policies.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1717"><display-text><sup>135</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_177"><page-start number="pg41"></page-start>Despite efforts to control access through its borders, sickly people inevitably slipped through the gates or found someone willing to row them across the Charles River to one of the many town docks. Whether they carried disease from towns in the hinterlands or from newly arrived ships is not known. We do know house quarantine was put to use within the first year after this landmark legislation, when Boston Selectmen granted the justices of the peace a warrant to remove Widow Paige and her family to a local quarantine house because it was feared they would spread smallpox. Six days later four of the selectmen recommended home confinement of Mr. John Jenkins’ African servant who was alleged to be infected with smallpox.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1719"><display-text><sup>136</sup></display-text></ref> These distinctively different approaches to quarantine were presumably motivated by fear of inadvertently spreading the pox (i.e., Widow Paige’s younger family members may have been harder to quarantine in a home environment than Mr. Jenkins’ servant). At a broader level, these isolation strategies confirmed the limitations of the colony’s quarantine program. Home isolation was the direct result of its lax enforcement of maritime quarantine. Failing to capture infected immigrants at Castle Island meant the selectmen needed an extensive number of expensive watchmen to monitor infected families in one of the most congested colonial ports in America. The chances for a successful containment of smallpox were constrained by a (1) limited number of watchmen, (2) the poorly managed interactions between infected families their watchmen and physicians, and (3) inadvertent contact with pox-contaminated blankets and other essential supplies that carried the pox virus into and out of infected homes.</p><p local-id="A6424C_178">These isolated cases soon blossomed into an epidemic in June 1701, but the first deaths did not occur until August. To stop its spread, the selectmen retained the services of the town watchmen. For example, the selectmen paid Thomas Davise twenty shillings, or at the rate of slightly more than one shilling a day, for watching the house of Henry Sharps for fifteen days.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1721"><display-text><sup>137</sup></display-text></ref> With hundreds dying and thousands infected, guards were not only expensive but few and far between; immunized guards were drawn from a limited number of elderly residents who had survived the epidemics of 1689 or 1693.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1723"><display-text><sup>138</sup></display-text></ref> By October, Cotton Mather, Boston’s famous Puritan evangelist, expressed the views of the populace when he proclaimed, “Smallpox is on every side of us.”<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1725"><display-text><sup>139</sup></display-text></ref> With few resources to contain and isolate the infected, the disease spread so rapidly that in December alone over eighty people died. The epidemic was soon out of control despite all efforts to contain it. Mather’s three children were placed in house quarantine. Surprising as it may seem, one hundred different watchmen were retained to care for these children’s needs. This extraordinary support, while somewhat unusual, and perhaps reflective of Mather’s higher station within the community, is an extreme example of the financial burdens created by home isolation.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1727"><display-text><sup>140</sup></display-text></ref> Given his exalted spiritual status, it may have been considered a badge of Christian generosity to <page-start number="pg42"></page-start>look out for Mather’s pox-infected children. The fact that his wife passed away on the first of December made his quarantine woes an even greater burden that would alter his fortunes as a minister and set him on a collision course with destiny seeking a scientific solution to the smallpox scourge. The epidemic may have infected as much as half the population and stretched resources to the limit, especially once the town adopted its labor-intensive home isolation strategy.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1729"><display-text><sup>141</sup></display-text></ref> The consequences of lax enforcement were significant. In 1702, a total of 313 persons, or 4.4 percent of Boston’s population, died from smallpox.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1731"><display-text><sup>142</sup></display-text></ref></p></section><section local-id="A6424C_179"><head>Birth of an Island Quarantine Hospital</head><p local-id="A6424C_180">As the town of Boston prospered from increased trade with the West Indies, South America, and Europe, imported cases of smallpox increased.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1733"><display-text><sup>143</sup></display-text></ref> Prior to 1715, attempts to isolate domestic cases of smallpox were handled by confining residents in private houses or in the town pest house located on Fort Hill, the former military garrison overlooking Boston. Despite its convenient location, many residents were less accepting of its insidious presence insisting the pest house be relocated fearing it spread disease.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1735"><display-text><sup>144</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_181">These concerns prompted a call for reforming provincial quarantine practices, including the nuisance of the town’s pest house. In September 1715, public interest in a safer quarantine location surfaced at a town meeting.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1737"><display-text><sup>145</sup></display-text></ref> After considerable delay, on June 11, 1716, a committee was appointed to identify a remote location for a quarantine hospital. After six months of deliberations, Spectacle Island and Squantum Neck were deemed the two most suitable locations. One of the factors that may have influenced their selection of sites was the fact that Samuel Bill, owner of Spectacle Island, had previously allowed his island to be used for quarantine with the consent of the provincial government.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1739"><display-text><sup>146</sup></display-text></ref> Despite this precedent, the committee narrowed its recommendation to a site on Squantum Neck.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1741"><display-text><sup>147</sup></display-text></ref> The House of Representatives accepted the committee’s report, and 150 pounds was set aside to purchase one acre on Squantum Neck, about six miles south of downtown Boston.</p><p local-id="A6424C_182">This decision was rejected by the inhabitants of Dorchester, Braintree, and Milton who were most immediately impacted by this location. The town’s inhabitants petitioned the House of Representatives that no hospital be built on Squantum Neck. Bowing to this public outcry, on April 11, 1717, a new committee, composed of Adam Winthrop, William Payne, Samuel Thaxter, and Jonathan Dowse, was appointed to find a more suitable hospital location.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1743"><display-text><sup>148</sup></display-text></ref> Adam Winthrop was the great-great-grandson of Governor John Winthrop and a member of the Governor’s Council.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1745"><display-text><sup>149</sup></display-text></ref> The others were all members of the House of Representatives with Dowse representing Charlestown, Thaxter representing Hingham, and Payne the town of Boston. Their selection underscored the importance the General Court placed on the views <page-start number="pg43"></page-start>of the town’s representatives in choosing the next quarantine station. After evaluating several sites, including Deer Island and Spectacle Island, their decision was almost a foregone conclusion. They established the southerly end of Spectacle Island for the quarantine hospital. In exchange, Samuel Bill and his wife received 100 pounds for their property. About two months later, the province reimbursed Bostonians for building the hospital by paying them 173 pounds for their efforts.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1747"><display-text><sup>150</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_183">Within a few weeks of the disbursement of funds and before the hospital could even be completed, some eighty passengers arrived in Boston Harbor with smallpox. In keeping with past practice, they were exiled to Spectacle Island. Since the facilities were not yet ready, at the request of the provincial government, Samuel Bill personally accommodated the sick on his half of the island. Unfortunately, their needs overwhelmed his resources, and in their desperate effort to survive on the island, they despoiled his property.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1749"><display-text><sup>151</sup></display-text></ref> In an attempt to literally “mend fences,” the General Court paid Bill for his troubles and even installed a fence to stop future invasions of his property.</p><p local-id="A6424C_184">Belatedly, the General Court opened Spectacle Island hospital on February 14, 1718.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1751"><display-text><sup>152</sup></display-text></ref> The ninety-seven-acre island, only four miles from Boston’s Long Wharf, was large enough to accommodate future development. Depending upon the level of the tide, Spectacle Island used to appear as two separate islands or as a pair of spectacles connected together by a short bar of land, which is how it got its name. It lies between Thompson’s Island and Long Island about two miles southwest of Deer Island, where Boston’s modern sewage plant now resides. One of its greatest advantages was it fell within the jurisdiction of Boston, thereby trumping past intermunicipal feuds concerning acceptable locations for a quarantine hospital. This island, along with Deer Island, Hogs Island, and Long Island,<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1753"><display-text><sup>153</sup></display-text></ref> had been granted to Boston in 1634 and was well positioned to receive ships coming into the harbor, since it had easy access to Boston services using chartered sail and rowboats.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1755"><display-text><sup>154</sup></display-text></ref></p><p local-id="A6424C_185">The offshore pest house wasn’t large enough to accommodate a shipload of infected passengers. At best, it could handle several dozen patients at a time operating on a shoe string budget while relying on the goodwill of its neighbor to cover unexpected costs, such as supporting some seventy Irish passengers quarantined for six weeks in November 1719.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1757"><display-text><sup>155</sup></display-text></ref> Yet, despite its limitations and the problematic honor system for disease reporting, the quarantine station’s existence reflected an emerging civic responsibility to meet the housing, health, and social needs of the victims.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1759"><display-text><sup>156</sup></display-text></ref> The provincial government recognized the value of a hospital even if their calculations underestimated its proper size and needs. Over time, the concept of needs would be extended to cover nurses, reliable boat service, reading materials, sanitary facilities, and rudimentary bathing facilities.</p><p local-id="A6424C_186">Boston had survived for eighty-eight years without a hospital for its own citizens. In 1718, population growth and the challenges of higher density <page-start number="pg44"></page-start>development forced legislators to rethink its house quarantine strategies and choose island isolation as the accepted mode of care. Coincidentally, this year also marked the beginning of regular stagecoach service between Boston and Rhode Island.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1761"><display-text><sup>157</sup></display-text></ref> While seemingly unrelated, these events were in fact linked. There was a growing awareness that Boston was not merely a thriving maritime port but also a town with growing trade relations with neighboring cities to the north, south, and west. Its population, estimated at 10,450 persons in 1718 found travel within the colony to be much easier than ever before, as old Indian trails were turned into wider paths that soon allowed passage by horse and carriage.<ref type="local-id" value="A6424C_1763"><display-text><sup>158</sup></display-text></ref> While most people walked on foot, the more affluent rode on horses or, if very wealthy, rode in a horse and buggy. Long distance travel was not easy and could be very exhausting, since early New England roads were nothing more than worn pathways over bare earth and became mud holes in the rainy season and impassable wastelands in the winter. Relatively poor provincial roads influenced the decision to locate the quarantine station offshore rather than in the hinterlands. Spectacle Island could be reached in a rowboat in several hours. More importantly, it could be reached without passing through any towns, avoiding political controversies associated with a location in Boston’s suburbs or the provincial hinterlands.</p></section></div><page-start number="pg45"></page-start></gpg-book>
